<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1//EN"> -->

<chapter id="administration">
  <title>Administering Bugzilla</title>
  <subtitle>
    Or, I just got this cool thing installed.  Now what the heck do I
    do with it?
  </subtitle>
  
  <para>
    So you followed <quote><xref linkend="installation"></quote> to the
    letter, and logged into Bugzilla for the very first time with your
    super-duper god account.  You sit, contentedly staring at the
    Bugzilla Query Screen, the worst of the whole mad business of
    installing this terrific program behind you. It seems, though, you
    have nothing yet to query! Your first act of business should be to
    setup the operating parameters for Bugzilla so you can get busy
    getting data into your bug tracker.
  </para>

  <section id="postinstall-check">
    <title>Post-Installation Checklist</title>
    <para>
      After installation, follow the checklist below to help ensure
      that you have a successful installation. If you do not see a
      recommended setting for a parameter, consider leaving it at the
      default while you perform your initial tests on your Bugzilla
      setup.
    </para>
      <indexterm>
	<primary>checklist</primary>
      </indexterm>
    <procedure>
      <step>
	<para>
	  Bring up <filename>editparams.cgi</filename> in your web
	  browser.  This should be available as the <quote>edit
	    parameters</quote> link from any Bugzilla screen once you
	  have logged in.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>The <quote>maintainer</quote> is the email address of
	  the person responsible for maintaining this Bugzilla
	  installation.  The maintainer need not be a valid Bugzilla
	  user.  Error pages, error emails, and administrative mail
	  will be sent with the maintainer as the return email
	  address.</para>
	<para>
	  Set <quote>maintainer</quote> to <emphasis>your</emphasis> email address.
	  This allows Bugzilla's error messages to display your email
	  address and allow people to contact you for help.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>The <quote>urlbase</quote> parameter defines the fully
	  qualified domain name and web server path to your Bugzilla
	  installation.</para>
	<para>
	  For example, if your bugzilla query page is
	  http://www.foo.com/bugzilla/query.cgi, set your
	  <quote>urlbase</quote> is http://www.foo.com/bugzilla/.  
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para><quote>usebuggroups</quote> dictates whether or not to
	  implement group-based security for Bugzilla.  If set,
	  Bugzilla bugs can have an associated groupmask defining
	  which groups of users are allowed to see and edit the
	  bug.</para>
	<para>
	  Set "usebuggroups" to "on" <emphasis>only</emphasis> if you
	  may wish to restrict access to products. I suggest leaving
	  this parameter <emphasis>off</emphasis> while initially
	  testing your Bugzilla.  
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>
	  <quote>usebuggroupsentry</quote>, when set to
	  <quote>on</quote>, requires that all bugs have an associated
	  groupmask when submitted.  This parameter is made for those
	  installations where product isolation is a necessity.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Set "usebuggroupsentry" to "on" if you absolutely need to
	  restrict access to bugs from the moment they are submitted
	  through resolution. Once again, if you are simply testing
	  your installation, I suggest against turning this parameter
	  on; the strict security checking may stop you from being
	  able to modify your new entries.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>
	  You run into an interesting problem when Bugzilla reaches a
	  high level of continuous activity.  MySQL supports only
	  table-level write locking.  What this means is that if
	  someone needs to make a change to a bug, they will lock the
	  entire table until the operation is complete.  Locking for
	  write also blocks reads until the write is complete.  The
	  <quote>shadowdb</quote> parameter was designed to get around
	  this limitation.  While only a single user is allowed to
	  write to a table at a time, reads can continue unimpeded on
	  a read-only shadow copy of the database.  Although your
	  database size will double, a shadow database can cause an
	  enormous performance improvement when implemented on
	  extremely high-traffic Bugzilla databases.
	</para>
        <para>
	  Set "shadowdb" to "bug_shadowdb" if you will be running a
	  *very* large installation of Bugzilla. The shadow database
	  enables many simultaneous users to read and write to the
	  database without interfering with one another.  
	  <note>
	    <para>
	      Enabling "shadowdb" can adversely affect the stability
	      of your installation of Bugzilla. You should regularly
	      check that your database is in sync.  It is often
	      advisable to force a shadow database sync nightly via
	      <quote>cron</quote>.
	    </para>
	  </note> Once again, in testing you should avoid this option
	  -- use it if or when you <emphasis>need</emphasis> to use
	  it, and have repeatedly run into the problem it was designed
	  to solve -- very long wait times while attempting to commit
	  a change to the database.  Mozilla.org began needing
	  <quote>shadowdb</quote> when they reached around 40,000
	  Bugzilla users with several hundred Bugzilla bug changes and
	  comments per day.
        </para>
	<para>
	  If you use the "shadowdb" option, it is only natural that
	  you should turn the "queryagainstshadowdb" option "On" as
	  well.  Otherwise you are replicating data into a shadow
	  database for no reason!
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para><quote>headerhtml</quote>, <quote>footerhtml</quote>,
	  <quote>errorhtml</quote>, <quote>bannerhtml</quote>, and
	  <quote>blurbhtml</quote> are all templates which control
	  display of headers, footers, errors, banners, and additional
	  data.  We could go into some detail regarding the usage of
	  these, but it is really best just to monkey around with them
	  a bit to see what they do.  I strongly recommend you copy
	  your <filename>data/params</filename> file somewhere safe
	  before playing with these values, though.  If they are
	  changed dramatically, it may make it impossible for you to
	  display Bugzilla pages to fix the problem until you have
	  restored your <filename>data/params</filename> file.</para>
        <para>
	  If you have custom logos or HTML you must put in place to
	  fit within your site design guidelines, place the code in
	  the "headerhtml", "footerhtml", "errorhtml", "bannerhtml",
	  or "blurbhtml" text boxes.
	  <note>
	    <para>
	      The "headerhtml" text box is the HTML printed out
	      <emphasis>before</emphasis> any other code on the page,
	      except the CONTENT-TYPE header sent by the Bugzilla
	      engine. If you have a special banner, put the code for
	      it in "bannerhtml". You may want to leave these settings
	      at the defaults initially.
	    </para>
	  </note>
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para><quote>passwordmail</quote> is rather simple.  Every
	  time a user creates an account, the text of this parameter
	  is read as the text to send to the new user along with their
	  password message.</para>
        <para>
	  Add any text you wish to the "passwordmail" parameter box.
	  For instance, many people choose to use this box to give a
	  quick training blurb about how to use Bugzilla at your site.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para><quote>useqacontact</quote> allows you to define an
	  email address for each component, in addition to that of the
	  default owner, who will be sent carbon copies of incoming
	  bugs.  The critical difference between a QA Contact and an
	  Owner is that the QA Contact follows the component.  If you
	  reassign a bug from component A to component B, the QA
	  Contact for that bug will change with the reassignment,
	  regardless of owner.</para>
	<para><quote>usestatuswhiteboard</quote> defines whether you
	  wish to have a free-form, overwritable field associated with
	  each bug.  The advantage of the Status Whiteboard is that it
	  can be deleted or modified with ease, and provides an
	  easily-searchable field for indexing some bugs that have
	  some trait in common.  Many people will put <quote>help
	    wanted</quote>, <quote>stalled</quote>, or <quote>waiting
	    on reply from somebody</quote> messages into the Status
	  Whiteboard field so those who peruse the bugs are aware of
	  their status even more than that which can be indicated by
	  the Resolution fields.</para>
	<para>
	  Do you want to use the QA Contact ("useqacontact") and
	  status whiteboard ("usestatuswhiteboard") fields? These
	  fields are useful because they allow for more flexibility,
	  particularly when you have an existing Quality Assurance
	  and/or Release Engineering team,  but they may not be needed
	  for many smaller installations.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>
	  Set "whinedays" to the amount of days you want to let bugs
	  go in the "New" or "Reopened" state before notifying people
	  they have untouched new bugs.  If you do not plan to use
	  this feature, simply do not set up the whining cron job
	  described in the installation instructions, or set this
	  value to "0" (never whine).
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para><quote>commenton</quote> fields allow you to dictate
	  what changes can pass without comment, and which must have a
	  comment from the person who changed them.  Often,
	  administrators will allow users to add themselves to the CC
	  list, accept bugs, or change the Status Whiteboard without
	  adding a comment as to their reasons for the change, yet
	  require that most other changes come with an
	  explanation.</para>
	<para>
	  Set the "commenton" options according to your site policy.
	  It is a wise idea to require comments when users resolve,
	  reassign, or reopen bugs at the very least.
	  <note>
	    <para>
	      It is generally far better to require a developer
	      comment when resolving bugs than not. Few things are
	      more annoying to bug database users than having a
	      developer mark a bug "fixed" without any comment as to
	      what the fix was (or even that it was truly fixed!)
	    </para>
	  </note>
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<para>The <quote>supportwatchers</quote> option can be an
	  exceptionally powerful tool in the hands of a power Bugzilla
	  user.  By enabling this option, you allow users to receive
	  email updates whenever other users receive email updates.
	  This is, of course, subject to the groupset restrictions on
	  the bug; if the <quote>watcher</quote> would not normally be
	  allowed to view a bug, the watcher cannot get around the
	  system by setting herself up to watch the bugs of someone
	  with bugs outside her priveleges.  She would still only
	  receive email updates for those bugs she could normally
	  view.</para>
	<para>For Bugzilla sites which require strong inter-Product
	  security to prevent snooping, watchers are not a good
	  idea.</para>
	<para>
	  However, for most sites you should set
	  <quote>supportwatchers</quote> to "On".  This feature is
	  helpful for team leads to monitor progress in their
	  respective areas, and can offer many other benefits, such as
	  allowing a developer to pick up a former engineer's bugs
	  without requiring her to change all the information in the
	  bug.
	</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>

  <section id="useradmin">
    <title>User Administration</title>
    <para>
      User administration is one of the easiest parts of Bugzilla.
      Keeping it from getting out of hand, however, can become a
      challenge.
    </para>

    <section id="defaultuser">
      <title>Creating the Default User</title>

      <para>
	When you first run checksetup.pl after installing Bugzilla, it
	will prompt you for the administrative username (email
	address) and password for this "super user". If for some
	reason you were to delete the "super user" account, re-running
	checksetup.pl will again prompt you for this username and
	password.
      </para>
      <tip>
	<para>
       If you wish to add more administrative users, you must use the
	  MySQL interface. Run "mysql" from the command line, and use
	  these commands ("mysql>" denotes the  mysql prompt, not
	  something you should type in):
	  <command><prompt>mysql></prompt> use bugs;</command>
	  <command><prompt>mysql></prompt> update profiles set
	    groupset=0x7ffffffffffffff where login_name = "(user's
	    login name)"; </command>
	</para>
	<para>Yes, that is <emphasis>fourteen</emphasis>
	  <quote>f</quote>'s.  A whole lot of f-ing going on if you
	  want to create a new administator.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section id="manageusers">
      <title>Managing Other Users</title>

      <section id="login">
	<title>Logging In</title>
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Open the index.html page for your Bugzilla installation
	      in your browser window.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click the "Query Existing Bug Reports" link.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click the "Log In" link at the foot of the page.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Type your email address, and the password which was
	      emailed to you when you created your Bugzilla account,
	      into the spaces provided.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>Congratulations, you are logged in!</para>
      </section>

      <section id="createnewusers">
	<title>Creating new users</title>
	<para>
	  Your users can create their own user accounts by clicking
	  the "New Account" link at the bottom of each page. However,
	  should you desire to create user accounts ahead of time,
	  here is how you do it.
	</para>
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      After logging in, click the "Users" link at the footer
	      of the query page.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      To see a specific user, type a portion of their login
	      name in the box provided and click "submit". To see all
	      users, simply click the "submit" button. You must click
	      "submit" here to be able to add a new user.
	    </para>
	    <tip>
	      <para>
		More functionality is available via the list on the
		right-hand side of the text entry box. You can match
		what you type as a case-insensitive substring (the
		default) of all users on your system, a case-sensitive
		regular expression (please see the <command>man
		  regexp</command> manual page for details on regular
		expression syntax), or a <emphasis>reverse</emphasis>
		regular expression match, where every user name which
		does NOT match the regular expression is selected.
	      </para>
	    </tip>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click the "Add New User" link at the bottom of the user
	      list
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Fill out the form presented.  This page is
	      self-explanatory.  When done, click "submit".
	    </para>
	    <note>
	      <para>
		Adding a user this way will <emphasis>not</emphasis>
		send an email informing them of their username and
		password. While useful for creating dummy accounts
		(watchers which shuttle mail to another system, for
		instance, or email addresses which are a mailing
		list), in general it is preferable to log out and use
		the <quote>New Account</quote> button to create users,
		as it will pre-populate all the required fields and
		also notify  the user of her account name and
		password.
	      </para>
	    </note>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="disableusers">
	<title>Disabling Users</title>
	<para>
	  I bet you noticed that big "Disabled Text" entry box
	  available from the "Add New User" screen, when you edit an
	  account? By entering any text in this box and selecting
	  "submit", you have prevented the user from using Bugzilla
	  via the web interface. Your explanation, written in this
	  text box, will be presented to the user the next time she
	  attempts to use the system.
	  <warning>
	    <para>
	      Don't disable your own administrative account, or you
	      will hate life!
	    </para>
	    <para>At this time, <quote>Disabled Text</quote> does not
	      prevent a user from using the email interface.  If you
	      have the email interface enabled, they can still
	      continue to submit bugs and comments that way.  We need
	      a patch to fix this.</para>
	  </warning>
	</para>
      </section>

      <section id="modifyusers">
	<title>Modifying Users</title>
	<para>
	  Here I will attempt to describe the function of each option
	  on the Edit User screen.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Login Name</emphasis>: This is generally the
	      user's email address. However, if you have edited your
	      system parameters, this may just be the user's login
	      name or some other identifier.
	      <tip>
		<para>
		  For compatability reasons, you should probably stick
		  with email addresses as user login names.  It will
		  make your life easier.
		</para>
	      </tip>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Real Name</emphasis>: Duh!
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Password</emphasis>:  You can change the user
	      password here.  It is normal to only see asterisks.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Email Notification</emphasis>: You may choose
	      from one of three options:
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    All qualifying bugs except those which I change:
		    The user will be notified of any change to any bug
		    for which she is the reporter, assignee, QA
		    Contact, CC recipient, or "watcher".
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Only those bugs which I am listed on the CC line:
		    The user will not be notified of changes to bugs
		    where she is the assignee, reporter, or QA
		    Contact, but will receive them if she is on the CC
		    list.
		    <note>
		      <para>
			She will still receive whining cron emails if
			you set up the "whinemail" feature.
		      </para>
		    </note>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    <emphasis>All Qualifying Bugs</emphasis>: This
		    user is a glutton for punishment. If her name is
		    in the reporter, QA Contact, CC, assignee, or is a
		    "watcher", she will get email updates regarding
		    the bug.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
</para>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Disable Text</emphasis>: If you type anything
	      in this box, including just a space, the user account is
	      disabled from making any changes to bugs via the web
	      interface, and what you type in this box is presented as
	      the reason.
	      <warning>
		<para>Don't disable the administrator account!</para>
	      </warning>
	      <note>
		<para>
		  As of this writing, the user can still submit bugs
		  via the e-mail gateway, if you set it up, despite
		  the disabled text field.  The e-mail gateway should
		  <emphasis>not</emphasis> be enabled for secure
		  installations of Bugzilla.
		</para>
	      </note>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>CanConfirm</emphasis>: This field is only used
	      if you have enabled "unconfirmed" status in your
	      parameters screen.  If you enable this for a user, that
	      user can then move bugs from "Unconfirmed" to
	      "Confirmed" status (e.g.: "New" status). Be judicious
	      about allowing users to turn this bit on for other
	      users.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Creategroups</emphasis>: This option will
	      allow a user to create and destroy groups in Bugzilla.
	      Unless you are using the Bugzilla GroupSentry security
	      option "usebuggroupsentry" in your parameters, this
	      setting has no effect.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Editbugs</emphasis>: Unless a user has this
	      bit set, they can only edit those bugs for which they
	      are the assignee or the reporter.  
	      <note>
		<para>
		  Leaving this option unchecked does not prevent users
		  from adding comments to a bug!  They simply cannot
		  change a bug priority, severity, etc. unless they
		  are the assignee or reporter.
		</para>
	      </note>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Editcomponents</emphasis>: This flag allows a
	      user to create new  products and components, as well as
	      modify and destroy those that have no bugs associated
	      with them.  If a product or component has bugs
	      associated with it, those bugs must be moved to a
	      different product or component before Bugzilla will
	      allow them to be destroyed.  The name of a product or
	      component can be changed without affecting the
	      associated bugs, but it tends to annoy the hell out of
	      your users when these change a lot.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Editkeywords</emphasis>: If you use Bugzilla's
	      keyword functionality, enabling this feature allows a
	      user can create and destroy keywords. As always, the
	      keywords for existing bugs containing the keyword the
	      user wishes to destroy must be changed before Bugzilla
	      will allow it to die. You must be very careful about
	      creating too many new keywords if you run a very large
	      Bugzilla installation; keywords are global variables
	      across products, and you can often run into a phenomenon
	      called "keyword bloat". This confuses users, and then
	      the feature goes unused.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Editusers</emphasis>: This flag allows a user
	      do what you're doing right now: edit other users. This
	      will allow those with the right to do so to remove
	      administrator priveleges from other users or grant them
	      to themselves.  Enable with care.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>PRODUCT</emphasis>: PRODUCT bugs access.  This
	      allows an administrator, with product-level granularity,
	      to specify in which products a user can edit bugs.  The
	      user must still have the "editbugs" privelege to edit
	      bugs in this area; this simply restricts them from even
	      seeing bugs outside these boundaries if the
	      administrator has enabled the group sentry parameter
	      "usebuggroupsentry".  Unless you are using bug groups,
	      this option has no effect.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="programadmin">
    <title>Product, Component, Milestone, and Version
      Administration</title>
    <epigraph>
      <para>
	Dear Lord, we have to get our users to do WHAT?
      </para>
    </epigraph>

    <section id="products">
      <title>Products</title>
      <subtitle>Formerly, and in some spots still, called
	"Programs"</subtitle>
      <para>
	<glossterm linkend="gloss_product" baseform="product">Products</glossterm> are
	the broadest category in Bugzilla, and you should have the
	least of these. If your company makes computer games, you
	should have one product per game, and possibly a few special
	products (website, meetings...)
      </para>
      <para>
	A Product (formerly called "Program", and still referred to
	that way in some portions of the source code) controls some
	very important functions. The number of "votes" available for
	users to vote for the most important bugs is set per-product,
	as is the number of votes required to move a bug automatically
	from the UNCONFIRMED status to the NEW status.  One can close
	a Product for further bug entry and define various Versions
	available from the Edit product screen.
      </para>
      <para>To create a new product:</para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Select "components" from the yellow footer
	  </para>
	  <tip>
	    <para>
	      It may seem counterintuitive to click "components" when
	      you want to edit the properties associated with
	      Products.  This is one of a long list of things we want
	      in Bugzilla 3.0...
	    </para>
	  </tip>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Select the "Add" link to the right of "Add a new product".
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Enter the name of the product and a description. The
	    Description field is free-form.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <tip>
	<para>
	  Don't worry about the "Closed for bug entry", "Maximum Votes
	  per person",  "Maximum votes a person can put on a single
	  bug", "Number of votes a bug in this Product needs to
	  automatically get out of the UNCOMFIRMED state", and
	  "Version" options yet. We'll cover those in a few moments.
	</para>
      </tip>
    </section>
    
    <section id="components">
      <title>Components</title>
      <para>
	Components are subsections of a Product. 

	<example>
	  <title>Creating some Components</title>
	  <informalexample>
	    <para>
	      The computer game you are designing may have a "UI"
	      component, an "API" component, a "Sound System"
	      component, and a "Plugins" component,  each overseen by
	      a different programmer.  It often makes sense to divide
	      Components in Bugzilla according to the natural
	      divisions of responsibility within your Product  or
	      company.
	    </para>
	  </informalexample>
	</example> Each component has a owner and (if you turned it on
	in the parameters), a QA  Contact. The owner should be the
	primary person who fixes bugs in that component.  The  QA
	Contact should be the person who will ensure these bugs are
	completely fixed. The Owner, QA Contact, and Reporter will get
	email when new bugs are created in this Component and when
	these bugs change. Default Owner and Default QA Contact fields
	only dictate the <emphasis>default assignments</emphasis>; the
	Owner and QA Contact fields in a bug  are otherwise unrelated
	to the Component.
      </para>

      <para>
	To create a new Component:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Select the "Edit components" link from the "Edit product"
	    page
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Select the "Add" link to the right of the "Add a new
	    component" text on the "Select Component" page.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Fill out the "Component" field, a short "Description", and
	    the "Initial Owner". The Component and Description fields
	    are free-form; the "Initial Owner" field must be that of a
	    user ID already existing in the database.  If the initial
	    owner does not exist, Bugzilla will refuse to create the
	    component.
	    <tip>
	      <para>
		Is your "Default Owner" a user who is not yet in the
		database? No problem.
		<orderedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Select the "Log out" link on the footer of the
		      page.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Select the "New Account" link on the footer of
		      the "Relogin" page
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Type in the email address of the default owner
		      you want to create in the "E-mail address"
		      field, and her full name in the "Real name"
		      field, then select the "Submit Query" button.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Now select "Log in" again, type in your login
		      information, and you can modify the product to
		      use the Default Owner information you require.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	      </para>
	    </tip>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Either Edit more components or return to the Bugzilla
	    Query Page. To return to the Product you were editing, you
	    must select the Components link as before.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section id="versions">
      <title>Versions</title>
      <para>
	Versions are the revisions of the product, such as "Flinders
	3.1", "Flinders 95", and "Flinders 2000".  Using Versions
	helps you isolate code changes and are an aid in reporting.

	<example>
	  <title>Common Use of Versions</title>
	  <informalexample>
	    <para>
	      A user reports a bug against Version "Beta 2.0" of your
	      product.  The current Version of your software is
	      "Release Candidate 1", and no longer has the bug.  This
	      will help you triage and classify bugs according to
	      their relevance.  It is also possible people may report
	      bugs against bleeding-edge beta versions that are not
	      evident in older versions of the software.  This can
	      help isolate code changes that caused the bug
	    </para>
	  </informalexample>
	</example>
	<example>
	  <title>A Different Use of Versions</title>
	  <informalexample>
	    <para>
	      This field has been used to good effect by an online
	      service provider in a slightly different way.  They had
	      three versions of the product: "Production", "QA", and
	      "Dev".  Although it may be the same product, a bug in
	      the development environment is not normally as critical
	      as a Production bug, nor does it need to be reported
	      publicly.  When used in conjunction with Target
	      Milestones, one can easily specify the environment where
	      a bug can be reproduced, and the Milestone by which it
	      will be fixed.
	    </para>
	  </informalexample>
	</example>
       </para>
      <para>
	To create and edit Versions:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    From the "Edit product" screen, select "Edit Versions"
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You will notice that the product already has the default
	    version "undefined". If your product doesn't use version
	    numbers, you may want to leave this as it is or edit it so
	    that it is "---". You can then go back to the edit
	    versions page and add new versions to your product.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Otherwise, click the "Add" button to the right of the "Add
	    a new version" text.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Enter the name of the Version.  This can be free-form
	    characters up to the limit of the text box.  Then select
	    the "Add" button.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    At this point you can select "Edit" to edit more Versions,
	    or return to the "Query" page, from which you can navigate
	    back to the product through the "components" link at the
	    foot of the Query page.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section id="milestones">
      <title>Milestones</title>
      <para>
	Milestones are "targets" that you plan to get a bug fixed by.
	For example, you have a bug that you plan to fix for your 3.0
	release, it would be assigned the milestone of 3.0. Or, you
	have a bug that you plan to fix for 2.8, this would have a
	milestone of 2.8.
      </para>
      <note>
	<para>
	  Milestone options will only appear for a Product if you
	  turned the "usetargetmilestone" field in the "Edit
	  Parameters" screen "On".
	</para>
      </note>
      <para>
	To create new Milestones, set Default Milestones, and set
	Milestone URL: 
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Select "edit milestones"
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Select "Add" to the right of the "Add a new milestone"
	    text
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Enter the name of the Milestone in the "Milestone" field.
	    You can optionally set the "Sortkey", which is a positive
	    or negative number (-255 to 255) that defines where in the
	    list this particular milestone appears. Select "Add".
	  </para>
	  <example>
	    <title>Using SortKey with Target Milestone</title>
	    <informalexample>
	      <para>
		Let's say you create a target milestone called
		"Release 1.0", with Sortkey set to "0". Later, you
		realize that you will have a public beta, called
		"Beta1". You can create a Milestone called "Beta1",
		with a Sortkey of "-1" in order to ensure people will
		see the Target Milestone of "Beta1" earlier on the
		list than "Release 1.0"
	      </para>
	    </informalexample>
	  </example>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If you want to add more milestones, select the "Edit"
	    link. If you don't, well shoot, you have to go back to the
	    "query" page and select "components" again, and make your
	    way back to the Product you were editing.
	    <note>
	      <para>
		This is another in the list of unusual user interface
		decisions that we'd like to get cleaned up.  Shouldn't
		there be a link to the effect of "edit the Product I
		was editing when I ended up here"?  In any case,
		clicking "components" in the footer takes you back to
		the "Select product" screen, from which you can begin
		editing your product again.
	      </para>
	    </note>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    From the Edit product screen again (once you've made your
	    way back), enter the URL for a description of what your
	    milestones are for this product in the "Milestone URL"
	    field. It should be of the format
	    "http://www.foo.com/bugzilla/product_milestones.html"
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Some common uses of this field include product
	    descriptions, product roadmaps, and of course a simple
	    description of the meaning of each milestone.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If you're using Target Milestones, the "Default Milestone"
	    field must have some kind of entry.  If you really don't
	    care if people set coherent Target Milestones,  simply
	    leave this at the default, "---".  However, controlling
	    and regularly updating the Default Milestone field is a
	    powerful tool when reporting the status of projects.
	  </para>
	  <para>Select the "Update" button when you are done.</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section id="voting">
      <title>Voting</title>
      <para>
	The concept of "voting" is a poorly understood, yet powerful
	feature for the management of open-source projects.  Each user
	is assigned so many Votes per product, which they can freely
	reassign (or assign multiple votes to a single bug). This
	allows developers to gauge user need for a particular
	enhancement or bugfix.  By allowing bugs with a certain number
	of votes to automatically move from "UNCONFIRMED" to "NEW",
	users of the bug system can help high-priority bugs garner
	attention so they don't sit for a long time awaiting triage.
      </para>
      <para>
	The daunting challenge of Votes is deciding where you draw the
	line for a "vocal majority".  If you only have a user base of
	100 users, setting a low threshold for bugs to move from
	UNCONFIRMED to NEW makes sense.  As the Bugzilla user base
	expands, however, these thresholds must be re-evaluated.  You
	should gauge whether this feature is worth the time and close
	monitoring involved, and perhaps forego implementation until
	you have a critical mass of users who demand it.
      </para>
      <para>To modify Voting settings:</para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Navigate to the "Edit product" screen for the Product you
	    wish to modify
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Set "Maximum Votes per person" to your calculated value.
	    Setting this field to "0" disables voting.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Set "Maximum Votes a person can put on a single bug" to
	    your calculated value.  It should probably be some number
	    lower than the "Maximum votes per person". Setting this
	    field to "0" disables voting, but leaves the voting
	    options open to the user.  This is confusing.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Set "Number of votes a bug in this product needs to
	    automatically get out of the UNCONFIRMED state" to your
	    calculated number.  Setting this field to "0"  disables
	    the automatic move of bugs from UNCONFIRMED to NEW.  Some
	    people advocate leaving this at "0", but of what use are
	    Votes if your Bugzilla user base is unable to affect which
	    bugs appear on Development radar?
	    <tip>
	      <para>
		You should probably set this number to higher than a
		small coalition of Bugzilla users can influence it.
		Most sites use this as a "referendum" mechanism -- if
		users are able to vote a bug out of UNCONFIRMED, it is
		a <emphasis>really</emphasis> bad bug!
	      </para>
	    </tip>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Once you have adjusted the values to your preference,
	    select the "Update" button.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>    

    <section id="groups">
      <title>Groups and Group Security</title>
      <para>
	Groups can be very useful in bugzilla, because they allow
	users to isolate bugs or products that should only be seen by
	certain people.  Groups can also be a complicated minefield of
	interdependencies and weirdness if mismanaged.

	<example>
	  <title>When to Use Group Security</title>
	  <informalexample>
	    <para>
	      Many Bugzilla sites isolate "Security-related" bugs from
	      all other bugs. This way, they can have a fix ready
	      before the security vulnerability is announced to the
	      world.  You can create a "Security" product which, by
	      default, has no members, and only add members to the
	      group (in their individual User page, as described under
	      User Administration) who should have priveleged access
	      to "Security" bugs.  Alternately, you may create a Group
	      independently of any Product, and change the Group mask
	      on individual bugs to restrict access to members only of
	      certain Groups.
	    </para>
	  </informalexample>
	</example> Groups only work if you enable the "usebuggroups"
	paramater. In addition, if the "usebuggroupsentry" parameter
	is "On", one can restrict access to products by groups, so
	that only members of a product group are able to view bugs
	within that product. Group security in Bugzilla can be divided
	into two categories: Generic and Product-Based.
      </para>
      <note>
	<para>
	  Groups in Bugzilla are a complicated beast that evolved out
	  of very simple user permission bitmasks, apparently itself
	  derived from common concepts in UNIX access controls.  A
	  "bitmask" is a fixed-length number whose value can describe
	  one, and only one, set of states.  For instance, UNIX file
	  permissions are assigned bitmask values:  "execute" has a
	  value of 1, "write" has a value of 2,  and "read" has a
	  value of 4.  Add them together, and a file can be read,
	  written to, and executed if it has a bitmask of "7". (This
	  is a simplified example -- anybody who knows UNIX security
	  knows there is much more to it than this.  Please bear with
	  me for the purpose of this note.)  The only way a bitmask
	  scheme can work is by doubling the bit count for each value.
	  Thus if UNIX wanted to offer another file permission, the
	  next would have to be a value of 8, then the next 16, the
	  next 32, etc.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Similarly, Bugzilla offers a bitmask to define group
	  permissions, with an internal limit of 64.  Several are
	  already occupied by built-in permissions.  The way around
	  this limitation is to avoid assigning groups to products if
	  you have many products, avoid bloating of group lists, and
	  religiously prune irrelevant groups.  In reality, most
	  installations of Bugzilla support far fewer than 64 groups,
	  so this limitation has not hit for most sites, but it is on
	  the table to be revised for Bugzilla 3.0 because it
	  interferes with the security schemes of some administrators.
	</para>
      </note>
      <para>
	To enable Generic Group Security ("usebuggroups"):
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Turn "On" "usebuggroups" in the "Edit Parameters" screen.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You will generally have no groups set up.  Select the
	    "groups" link in the footer.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Take a moment to understand the instructions on the "Edit
	    Groups" screen. Once you feel confident you understand
	    what is expected of you, select the "Add Group" link.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Fill out the "New Name" (remember, no spaces!), "New
	    Description", and "New User RegExp" fields.  "New User
	    RegExp" allows you to automatically place all users who
	    fulfill the Regular Expression into the new group.

	    <example>
	      <title>Creating a New Group</title>
	      <informalexample>
		<para>
		  I created a group called DefaultGroup with a
		  description of <quote>This is simply a group to play
		  with</quote>, and a New User RegExp of <quote>.*@mydomain.tld</quote>.
		  This new group automatically includes all Bugzilla
		  users with "@mydomain.tld" at the end of their user id.
		  When I finished, my new group was assigned bit #128.
		</para>
	      </informalexample>
	    </example> When you have finished, select the Add
	    button.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>
	To enable Product-Based Group Security (usebuggroupsentry):
      </para>
      <warning>
	<para>
	  Don't forget that you only have 64 groups masks available,
	  total, for your installation of Bugzilla!  If you plan on
	  having more than 50 products in your individual Bugzilla
	  installation, and require group security for your products,
	  you should consider either running multiple Bugzillas or
	  using Generic Group Security instead of Product-Based
	  ("usebuggroupsentry") Group Security.
	</para>
      </warning>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Turn "On" "usebuggroups" and "usebuggroupsentry" in the
	    "Edit Parameters" screen.
	  </para>
	  <warning>
	    <para>
	      "usebuggroupsentry" has the capacity to prevent the
	      administrative user from directly altering bugs because
	      of conflicting group permissions. If you plan on using
	      "usebuggroupsentry", you should plan on restricting
	      administrative account usage to administrative duties
	      only. In other words, manage bugs with an unpriveleged
	      user account, and manage users, groups, Products, etc.
	      with the administrative account.
	    </para>
	  </warning>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You will generally have no Groups set up, unless you
	    enabled "usebuggroupsentry" prior to creating any
	    Products.  To create "Generic Group Security" groups,
	    follow the instructions given above.  To create
	    Product-Based Group security, simply follow the
	    instructions for creating a new Product.  If you need to
	    add users to these new groups as you create them, you will
	    find the option to add them to the group available under
	    the "Edit User" screens.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
	You may find this example illustrative for how bug groups work.
	<example>
	  <title>Bugzilla Groups</title>
	  <literallayout>
Bugzilla Groups example
-----------------------

For this example, let us suppose we have four groups, call them
Group1, Group2, Group3, and Group4.

We have 5 users, User1, User2, User3, User4, User5.

We have 8 bugs, Bug1, ..., Bug8.

Group membership is defined by this chart:
(X denotes that user is in that group.)
(I apologize for the nasty formatting of this table.  Try viewing
it in a text-based browser or something for now. -MPB)

      G G G G
      r r r r
      o o o o
      u u u u
      p p p p
      1 2 3 4
     +-+-+-+-+
User1|X| | | |
     +-+-+-+-+
User2| |X| | |
     +-+-+-+-+
User3|X| |X| |
     +-+-+-+-+
User4|X|X|X| |
     +-+-+-+-+
User5| | | | |
     +-+-+-+-+

Bug restrictions are defined by this chart:
(X denotes that bug is restricted to that group.)

     G G G G
     r r r r
     o o o o
     u u u u
     p p p p
     1 2 3 4
    +-+-+-+-+
Bug1| | | | |
    +-+-+-+-+
Bug2| |X| | |
    +-+-+-+-+
Bug3| | |X| |
    +-+-+-+-+
Bug4| | | |X|
    +-+-+-+-+
Bug5|X|X| | |
    +-+-+-+-+
Bug6|X| |X| |
    +-+-+-+-+
Bug7|X|X|X| |
    +-+-+-+-+
Bug8|X|X|X|X|
    +-+-+-+-+

Who can see each bug?

Bug1 has no group restrictions.  Therefore, Bug1 can be seen by any
user, whatever their group membership.  This is going to be the only
bug that User5 can see, because User5 isn't in any groups.

Bug2 can be seen by anyone in Group2, that is User2 and User4.

Bug3 can be seen by anyone in Group3, that is User3 and User4.

Bug4 can be seen by anyone in Group4.  Nobody is in Group4, so none of
these users can see Bug4.

Bug5 can be seen by anyone who is in _both_ Group1 and Group2.  This
is only User4.  User1 cannot see it because he is not in Group2, and
User2 cannot see it because she is not in Group1.

Bug6 can be seen by anyone who is in both Group1 and Group3.  This
would include User3 and User4.  Similar to Bug5, User1 cannot see Bug6
because he is not in Group3.

Bug7 can be seen by anyone who is in Group1, Group2, and Group3.  This
is only User4.  All of the others are missing at least one of those
group priveleges, and thus cannot see the bug.

Bug8 can be seen by anyone who is in Group1, Group2, Group3, and
Group4.  There is nobody in all four of these groups, so nobody can
see Bug8.  It doesn't matter that User4 is in Group1, Group2, and
Group3, since he isn't in Group4.
	  </literallayout>
	</example>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="security">
    <title>Bugzilla Security</title>
    <epigraph>
      <para>
	Putting your money in a wall safe is better protection than
	depending on the fact that no one knows that you hide your
	money in a mayonnaise jar in your fridge.
      </para>
    </epigraph>
    <note>
      <para>
	Poorly-configured MySQL, Bugzilla, and FTP installations have
	given attackers full access to systems in the past.  Please
	take these guidelines seriously, even for Bugzilla machines
	hidden away behind your firewall.  80% of all computer
	trespassers are insiders, not anonymous crackers.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      Secure your installation.
      <note>
	<para>
	  These instructions must, of necessity, be somewhat vague
	  since Bugzilla runs on so many different platforms.  If you
	  have refinements of these directions for specific platforms,
	  please submit them to <ulink url="mailto://mozilla-webtools@mozilla.org">mozilla-webtools@mozilla.org</ulink>
	</para>
      </note>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Ensure you are running at least MysQL version 3.22.32 or
	    newer.  Earlier versions had notable security holes and
	    poorly secured default configuration choices.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>There is no substitute for understanding the
	      tools on your system!</emphasis> Read <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com/documentation/mysql/bychapter/manual_Privilege_system.html"> The MySQL Privilege System</ulink> until you can recite it from memory!</para>
	  <para>
	    At the very least, ensure you password the "mysql -u root"
	    account and the "bugs" account, establish grant table
	    rights (consult the Keystone guide in Appendix C: The
	    Bugzilla Database for some easy-to-use details) that do
	    not allow CREATE, DROP, RELOAD, SHUTDOWN, and PROCESS for
	    user "bugs".  I wrote up the Keystone advice back when I
	    knew far less about security than I do now : )
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Lock down /etc/inetd.conf.  Heck, disable inet entirely on
	    this box.  It should only listen to port 25 for Sendmail
	    and port 80 for Apache.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Do not run Apache as <quote>nobody</quote>.  This will
	    require very lax permissions in your Bugzilla directories.
	    Run it, instead, as a user with a name, set via your
	    httpd.conf file.
	    <note>
	      <para>
		<quote>nobody</quote> is a real user on UNIX systems.
		Having a process run as user id <quote>nobody</quote>
		is absolutely no protection against system crackers
		versus using any other user account.  As a general
		security measure, I recommend you create unique user
		ID's for each daemon running on your system and, if
		possible, use "chroot" to jail that process away from
		the rest of your system.
	      </para>
	    </note>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Ensure you have adequate access controls for the
	    $BUGZILLA_HOME/data/ and $BUGZILLA_HOME/shadow/
	    directories, as well as the $BUGZILLA_HOME/localconfig and
	    $BUGZILLA_HOME/globals.pl files. The localconfig file
	    stores your "bugs" user password, which would be terrible
	    to have in the hands of a criminal, while the "globals.pl"
	    stores some default information regarding your
	    installation which could aid a system cracker. In
	    addition, some files under $BUGZILLA_HOME/data/ store
	    sensitive information, and $BUGZILLA_HOME/shadow/ stores
	    bug information for faster retrieval.  If you fail to
	    secure these directories and this file, you will expose
	    bug information to those who may not be allowed to see it.
	  </para>
	  <note>
	    <para>
	      Bugzilla provides default .htaccess files to protect the
	      most common Apache installations.  However, you should
	      verify these are adequate according to the site-wide
	      security policy of your web server, and ensure that the
	      .htaccess files are allowed to "override" default
	      permissions set in your Apache configuration files.
	      Covering Apache security is beyond the scope of this
	      Guide; please consult the Apache documentation for
	      details.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      If you are using a web server that does not support the
	      .htaccess control method, <emphasis>you are at
		risk!</emphasis>  After installing, check to see if
	      you can view the file "localconfig" in your web browser
	      (e.g.:  <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/localconfig"> http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/localconfig</ulink>).  If you can read the contents of this file, your web server has not secured your bugzilla directory properly and you must fix this problem before deploying Bugzilla.  If, however, it gives you a "Forbidden" error, then it probably respects the .htaccess conventions and you are good to go.
	    </para>
	  </note>
	  <para>
	    On Apache, you can use .htaccess files to protect access
	    to these directories, as outlined in <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=57161">Bug 57161</ulink> for the localconfig file, and <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=65572"> Bug 65572</ulink> for adequate protection in your data/ and shadow/ directories.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Note the instructions which follow are Apache-specific.
	    If you use IIS, Netscape, or other non-Apache web servers,
	    please consult your system documentation for how to secure
	    these files from being transmitted to curious users.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Place the following text into a file named ".htaccess",
	    readable by your web server, in your $BUGZILLA_HOME/data
	    directory. <literallayout> &lt;Files comments&gt; allow
	      from all &lt;/Files&gt; deny from all </literallayout>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Place the following text into a file named ".htaccess",
	    readable by your web server, in your $BUGZILLA_HOME/
	    directory. <literallayout> &lt;Files localconfig&gt; deny
	      from all &lt;/Files&gt; allow from all </literallayout>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Place the following text into a file named ".htaccess",
	    readable by your web server, in your $BUGZILLA_HOME/shadow
	    directory. <literallayout> deny from all </literallayout>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-auto-insert-required-elements:t
sgml-balanced-tag-edit:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-namecase-general:t
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-parent-document:("Bugzilla-Guide.sgml" "book" "chapter")
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-tag-region-if-active:t
End:
-->
