<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1//EN"> -->
<chapter id="administration">
  <title>Administering Bugzilla</title>

  <section id="parameters">
    <title>Bugzilla Configuration</title>

    <para>Bugzilla is configured by changing various parameters, accessed
    from the "Edit parameters" link in the page footer. Here are
    some of the key parameters on that page. You should run down this
    list and set them appropriately after installing Bugzilla.</para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>checklist</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para> 
        <command>maintainer</command>:
        The maintainer parameter is the email address of the person 
        responsible for maintaining this
        Bugzilla installation. The address need not be that of a valid Bugzilla
        account.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>urlbase</command>:
        This parameter defines the fully qualified domain name and web 
        server path to your Bugzilla installation.</para>

        <para>For example, if your Bugzilla query page is
        <filename>http://www.foo.com/bugzilla/query.cgi</filename>, 
        set your <quote>urlbase</quote>
        to <filename>http://www.foo.com/bugzilla/</filename>.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>makeproductgroups</command>:
        This dictates whether or not to automatically create groups
        when new products are created.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>useentrygroupdefault</command>:
        Bugzilla products can have a group associated with them, so that
        certain users can only see bugs in certain products. When this 
        parameter is set to <quote>on</quote>, this 
        causes the initial group controls on newly created products 
        to place all newly-created bugs in the group 
        having the same name as the product immediately.
        After a product is initially created, the group controls
        can be further adjusted without interference by 
        this mechanism.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>shadowdb</command>:
        You run into an interesting problem when Bugzilla reaches a
        high level of continuous activity. MySQL supports only table-level
        write locking. What this means is that if someone needs to make a
        change to a bug, they will lock the entire table until the operation
        is complete. Locking for write also blocks reads until the write is
        complete. Note that more recent versions of mysql support row level
        locking using different table types. These types are slower than the
        standard type, and Bugzilla does not yet take advantage of features
        such as transactions which would justify this speed decrease. The
        Bugzilla team are, however, happy to hear about any experiences with
        row level locking and Bugzilla</para>

        <para>The <quote>shadowdb</quote>
        parameter was designed to get around this limitation. While only a
        single user is allowed to write to a table at a time, reads can
        continue unimpeded on a read-only shadow copy of the database.
        Although your database size will double, a shadow database can cause
        an enormous performance improvement when implemented on extremely
        high-traffic Bugzilla databases.</para>
        
        <para>
        As a guide, mozilla.org began needing 
        <quote>shadowdb</quote>
        when they reached around 40,000 Bugzilla users with several hundred
        Bugzilla bug changes and comments per day.</para>

        <para>The value of the parameter defines the name of the 
        shadow bug database. You will need to set the host and port settings
        from the params page, and set up replication in your database server
        so that updates reach this readonly mirror. Consult your database
        documentation for more detail.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>shutdownhtml</command>:

        If you need to shut down Bugzilla to perform administration, enter
        some descriptive HTML here and anyone who tries to use Bugzilla will
        receive a page to that effect. Obviously, editparams.cgi will
        still be accessible so you can remove the HTML and re-enable Bugzilla.
        :-)
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>passwordmail</command>:

        Every time a user creates an account, the text of
        this parameter (with substitutions) is sent to the new user along with
        their password message.</para>

        <para>Add any text you wish to the "passwordmail" parameter box. For
        instance, many people choose to use this box to give a quick training
        blurb about how to use Bugzilla at your site.</para>
      </step>


      <step>
        <para>
	<command>movebugs</command>:

	This option is an undocumented feature to allow moving bugs
	between separate Bugzilla installations.  You will need to understand
	the source code in order to use this feature.  Please consult
	<filename>movebugs.pl</filename> in your Bugzilla source tree for
	further documentation, such as it is.
	</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>useqacontact</command>:

        This allows you to define an email address for each component, in
        addition
        to that of the default owner, who will be sent carbon copies of
        incoming bugs.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
        <command>usestatuswhiteboard</command>:
        This defines whether you wish to have a free-form, overwritable field
        associated with each bug. The advantage of the Status Whiteboard is
        that it can be deleted or modified with ease, and provides an
        easily-searchable field for indexing some bugs that have some trait
        in common.         
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>whinedays</command>:
        Set this to the number of days you want to let bugs go
        in the NEW or REOPENED state before notifying people they have
        untouched new bugs. If you do not plan to use this feature, simply do
        not set up the whining cron job described in the installation
        instructions, or set this value to "0" (never whine).</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>commenton*</command>:
        All these
        fields allow you to dictate what changes can pass without comment,
        and which must have a comment from the person who changed them.
        Often, administrators will allow users to add themselves to the CC
        list, accept bugs, or change the Status Whiteboard without adding a
        comment as to their reasons for the change, yet require that most
        other changes come with an explanation.</para>

        <para>Set the "commenton" options according to your site policy. It
        is a wise idea to require comments when users resolve, reassign, or
        reopen bugs at the very least. 
        <note>
          <para>It is generally far better to require a developer comment
          when resolving bugs than not. Few things are more annoying to bug
          database users than having a developer mark a bug "fixed" without
          any comment as to what the fix was (or even that it was truly
          fixed!)</para>
        </note>
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>supportwatchers</command>:

        Turning on this option allows users to ask to receive copies of 
        all a particular other user's bug email. This is, of
        course, subject to the groupset restrictions on the bug; if the 
        <quote>watcher</quote>
        would not normally be allowed to view a bug, the watcher cannot get
        around the system by setting herself up to watch the bugs of someone
        with bugs outside her privileges. They would still only receive email
        updates for those bugs she could normally view.</para>        
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>

  <section id="useradmin">
    <title>User Administration</title>

    <section id="defaultuser">
      <title>Creating the Default User</title>

      <para>When you first run checksetup.pl after installing Bugzilla, it
      will prompt you for the administrative username (email address) and
      password for this "super user". If for some reason you delete
      the "super user" account, re-running checksetup.pl will again prompt
      you for this username and password.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>If you wish to add more administrative users, add them to 
        the "admin" group and, optionally, add edit the tweakparams, editusers,
        creategroups, editcomponents, and editkeywords groups to add the
        entire admin group to those groups.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section id="manageusers">
      <title>Managing Other Users</title>

      <section id="createnewusers">
        <title>Creating new users</title>

        <para>Your users can create their own user accounts by clicking the
        "New Account" link at the bottom of each page (assuming they
        aren't logged in as someone else already.) However, should you
        desire to create user accounts ahead of time, here is how you do
        it.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>After logging in, click the "Users" link at the footer of
            the query page, and then click "Add a new user".</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Fill out the form presented. This page is self-explanatory.
            When done, click "Submit".</para>

            <note>
              <para>Adding a user this way will 
              <emphasis>not</emphasis>

              send an email informing them of their username and password.
              While useful for creating dummy accounts (watchers which
              shuttle mail to another system, for instance, or email
              addresses which are a mailing list), in general it is
              preferable to log out and use the 
              <quote>New Account</quote>

              button to create users, as it will pre-populate all the
              required fields and also notify the user of her account name
              and password.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="modifyusers">
        <title>Modifying Users</title>

        <para>To see a specific user, search for their login name
        in the box provided on the "Edit Users" page. To see all users, 
        leave the box blank.</para>

        <para>You can search in different ways the listbox to the right
        of the text entry box. You can match by 
        case-insensitive substring (the default),
        regular expression, or a 
        <emphasis>reverse</emphasis>
        regular expression match, which finds every user name which does NOT
        match the regular expression. (Please see
        the <command>man regexp</command>
        manual page for details on regular expression syntax.)
        </para>

        <para>Once you have found your user, you can change the following
        fields:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>Login Name</emphasis>: 
            This is generally the user's full email address. However, if you
            have are using the emailsuffix Param, this may just be the user's
            login name. Note that users can now change their login names
            themselves (to any valid email address.)
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>Real Name</emphasis>: The user's real name. Note that
            Bugzilla does not require this to create an account.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>Password</emphasis>: 
            You can change the user's password here. Users can automatically
            request a new password, so you shouldn't need to do this often.
            If you want to disable an account, see Disable Text below.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>Disable Text</emphasis>: 
            If you type anything in this box, including just a space, the
            user is prevented from logging in, or making any changes to 
            bugs via the web interface. 
            The HTML you type in this box is presented to the user when
            they attempt to perform these actions, and should explain
            why the account was disabled.
            <warning>
              <para>Don't disable the administrator account!</para>
            </warning>

            <note>
              <para>The user can still submit bugs via
              the e-mail gateway, if you set it up, even if the disabled text
              field is filled in. The e-mail gateway should 
              <emphasis>not</emphasis>
              be enabled for secure installations of Bugzilla.</para>
            </note>
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>&lt;groupname&gt;</emphasis>: 
            If you have created some groups, e.g. "securitysensitive", then
            checkboxes will appear here to allow you to add users to, or
            remove them from, these groups.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>canconfirm</emphasis>: 
            This field is only used if you have enabled the "unconfirmed"
            status. If you enable this for a user,
            that user can then move bugs from "Unconfirmed" to a "Confirmed"
            status (e.g.: "New" status).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>creategroups</emphasis>: 
            This option will allow a user to create and destroy groups in
            Bugzilla.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>editbugs</emphasis>: 
            Unless a user has this bit set, they can only edit those bugs
            for which they are the assignee or the reporter. Even if this
            option is unchecked, users can still add comments to bugs.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>editcomponents</emphasis>: 
            This flag allows a user to create new products and components,
            as well as modify and destroy those that have no bugs associated
            with them. If a product or component has bugs associated with it,
            those bugs must be moved to a different product or component
            before Bugzilla will allow them to be destroyed.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>editkeywords</emphasis>: 
            If you use Bugzilla's keyword functionality, enabling this
            feature allows a user to create and destroy keywords. As always,
            the keywords for existing bugs containing the keyword the user
            wishes to destroy must be changed before Bugzilla will allow it
            to die.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>editusers</emphasis>: 
            This flag allows a user to do what you're doing right now: edit
            other users. This will allow those with the right to do so to
            remove administrator privileges from other users or grant them to
            themselves. Enable with care.</para>
          </listitem>


          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>tweakparams</emphasis>: 
            This flag allows a user to change Bugzilla's Params 
            (using <filename>editparams.cgi</filename>.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>&lt;productname&gt;</emphasis>: 
            This allows an administrator to specify the products in which 
            a user can see bugs. The user must still have the 
            "editbugs" privilege to edit bugs in these products.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="programadmin">
    <title>Product, Component, Milestone, and Version Administration</title>

    <section id="products">
      <title>Products</title>

      <para>
      <glossterm linkend="gloss-product" baseform="product">
      Products</glossterm>

      are the broadest category in Bugzilla, and tend to represent real-world
      shipping products. E.g. if your company makes computer games, 
      you should have one product per game, perhaps a "Common" product for 
      units of technology used in multiple games, and maybe a few special
       products (Website, Administration...)</para>

      <para>Many of Bugzilla's settings are configurable on a per-product
      basis. The number of "votes" available to users is set per-product, 
      as is the number of votes
      required to move a bug automatically from the UNCONFIRMED status to the
      NEW status.</para>

      <para>To create a new product:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select "products" from the footer</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the "Add" link in the bottom right</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the name of the product and a description. The
          Description field may contain HTML.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Don't worry about the "Closed for bug entry", "Maximum Votes
      per person", "Maximum votes a person can put on a single bug",
      "Number of votes a bug in this Product needs to automatically get out
      of the UNCOMFIRMED state", and "Version" options yet. We'll cover
      those in a few moments.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="components">
      <title>Components</title>

      <para>Components are subsections of a Product. E.g. the computer game 
      you are designing may have a "UI"
      component, an "API" component, a "Sound System" component, and a
      "Plugins" component, each overseen by a different programmer. It
      often makes sense to divide Components in Bugzilla according to the
      natural divisions of responsibility within your Product or
      company.</para>
      
      <para>
      Each component has a owner and (if you turned it on in the parameters),
      a QA Contact. The owner should be the primary person who fixes bugs in
      that component. The QA Contact should be the person who will ensure
      these bugs are completely fixed. The Owner, QA Contact, and Reporter
      will get email when new bugs are created in this Component and when
      these bugs change. Default Owner and Default QA Contact fields only
      dictate the 
      <emphasis>default assignments</emphasis>; 
      these can be changed on bug submission, or at any later point in
      a bug's life.</para>

      <para>To create a new Component:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the "Edit components" link from the "Edit product"
          page</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the "Add" link in the bottom right.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fill out the "Component" field, a short "Description", 
          the "Initial Owner" and "Initial QA Contact" (if enabled.) 
          The Component and Description fields may contain HTML; 
          the "Initial Owner" field must be a login name
          already existing in the database. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="versions">
      <title>Versions</title>

      <para>Versions are the revisions of the product, such as "Flinders
      3.1", "Flinders 95", and "Flinders 2000". Version is not a multi-select
      field; the usual practice is to select the most recent version with
      the bug.
      </para>

      <para>To create and edit Versions:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the "Edit product" screen, select "Edit Versions"</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You will notice that the product already has the default
          version "undefined". Click the "Add" link in the bottom right.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the name of the Version. This field takes text only. 
          Then click the "Add" button.</para>
        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="milestones">
      <title>Milestones</title>

      <para>Milestones are "targets" that you plan to get a bug fixed by. For
      example, you have a bug that you plan to fix for your 3.0 release, it
      would be assigned the milestone of 3.0.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Milestone options will only appear for a Product if you turned
        on the "usetargetmilestone" Param in the "Edit Parameters" screen.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>To create new Milestones, set Default Milestones, and set
      Milestone URL:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select "Edit milestones" from the "Edit product" page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select "Add" in the bottom right corner.
          text</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the name of the Milestone in the "Milestone" field. You
          can optionally set the "sortkey", which is a positive or negative
          number (-255 to 255) that defines where in the list this particular
          milestone appears. This is because milestones often do not 
          occur in alphanumeric order For example, "Future" might be
          after "Release 1.2". Select "Add".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>From the Edit product screen, you can enter the URL of a 
          page which gives information about your milestones and what
          they mean. </para>

        <tip>
          <para>If you want your milestone document to be restricted so
          that it can only be viewed by people in a particular Bugzilla
          group, the best way is to attach the document to a bug in that
          group, and make the URL the URL of that attachment.</para>
        </tip>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="voting">
    <title>Voting</title>

    <para>Voting allows users to be given a pot of votes which they can allocate
    to bugs, to indicate that they'd like them fixed. 
    This allows developers to gauge
    user need for a particular enhancement or bugfix. By allowing bugs with
    a certain number of votes to automatically move from "UNCONFIRMED" to
    "NEW", users of the bug system can help high-priority bugs garner
    attention so they don't sit for a long time awaiting triage.</para>

    <para>To modify Voting settings:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Navigate to the "Edit product" screen for the Product you
        wish to modify</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Maximum Votes per person</emphasis>:
        Setting this field to "0" disables voting.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Maximum Votes a person can put on a single
         bug"</emphasis>: 
         It should probably be some number lower than the
        "Maximum votes per person". Don't set this field to "0" if
        "Maximum votes per person" is non-zero; that doesn't make
        any sense.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Number of votes a bug in this product needs to
        automatically get out of the UNCONFIRMED state</emphasis>: 
        Setting this field to "0" disables the automatic move of
        bugs from UNCONFIRMED to NEW. 
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Once you have adjusted the values to your preference, click
        "Update".</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="groups">
    <title>Groups and Group Security</title>

    <para>Groups allow the administrator
    to isolate bugs or products that should only be seen by certain people.
    The association between products and groups is controlled from
    the product edit page under <quote>Edit Group Controls.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
    If the makeproductgroups param is on, a new group will be automatically
    created for every new product.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    On the product edit page, there is a page to edit the 
    <quote>Group Controls</quote> 
    for a product and determine which groups are applicable, default, 
    and mandatory for each product as well as controlling entry 
    for each product and being able to set bugs in a product to be 
    totally read-only unless some group restrictions are met. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
    For each group, it is possible to specify if membership in that
    group is...
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        required for bug entry, 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Not applicable to this product(NA),
        a possible restriction for a member of the 
        group to place on a bug in this product(Shown),
        a default restriction for a member of the 
        group to place on a bug in this product(Default),
        or a mandatory restriction to be placed on bugs 
        in this product(Mandatory).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Not applicable by non-members to this product(NA),
        a possible restriction for a non-member of the 
        group to place on a bug in this product(Shown),
        a default restriction for a non-member of the 
        group to place on a bug in this product(Default),
        or a mandatory restriction to be placed on bugs 
        in this product when entered by a non-member(Mandatory).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        required in order to make <emphasis>any</emphasis> change
        to bugs in this product <emphasis>including comments.</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>To create Groups:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the <quote>groups</quote>
        link in the footer.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Take a moment to understand the instructions on the <quote>Edit
        Groups</quote> screen, then select the <quote>Add Group</quote> link.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fill out the <quote>Group</quote>, <quote>Description</quote>, 
         and <quote>User RegExp</quote> fields. 
         <quote>User RegExp</quote> allows you to automatically
         place all users who fulfill the Regular Expression into the new group. 
         When you have finished, click <quote>Add</quote>.</para>
         <warning>
           <para>The User Regexp is a perl regexp and, if not anchored, will match 
           any part of an address.  So, if you do not want to grant access
           into 'mycompany.com' to 'badperson@mycompany.com.hacker.net', use 
           '@mycompany\.com$' as the regexp.</para>
         </warning>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>After you add your new group, edit the new group.  On the
        edit page, you can specify other groups that should be included
        in this group and which groups should be permitted to add and delete
        users from this group.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      Note that group permissions are such that you need to be a member
      of <emphasis>all</emphasis> the groups a bug is in, for whatever
      reason, to see that bug. Similarly, you must be a member 
      of <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the entry groups for a product 
      to add bugs to a product and you must be a member 
      of <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the canedit groups for a product
      in order to make <emphasis>any</emphasis> change to bugs in that
      product.
    </para>    
  </section>


  <section id="security">
    <title>Bugzilla Security</title>

    <warning>
      <para>Poorly-configured MySQL and Bugzilla installations have
      given attackers full access to systems in the past. Please take these
      guidelines seriously, even for Bugzilla machines hidden away behind
      your firewall. 80% of all computer trespassers are insiders, not
      anonymous crackers.</para>
    </warning>

    <note>
      <para>These instructions must, of necessity, be somewhat vague since
      Bugzilla runs on so many different platforms. If you have refinements
      of these directions for specific platforms, please submit them to 
      <ulink url="mailto://mozilla-webtools@mozilla.org">
      mozilla-webtools@mozilla.org</ulink>
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>To secure your installation:
     
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>There is no substitute for understanding the tools on your
        system!</emphasis>

        Read 
        <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/P/r/Privilege_system.html">
        The MySQL Privilege System</ulink>
        until you can recite it from memory!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Lock down <filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename>. Heck, disable
        inet entirely on this box. It should only listen to port 25 for
        Sendmail and port 80 for Apache.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Do not run Apache as 
        <quote>nobody</quote>

        . This will require very lax permissions in your Bugzilla
        directories. Run it, instead, as a user with a name, set via your
        httpd.conf file. 
        <note>
          <para>
          <quote>nobody</quote>

          is a real user on UNIX systems. Having a process run as user id 
          <quote>nobody</quote>

          is absolutely no protection against system crackers versus using
          any other user account. As a general security measure, I recommend
          you create unique user ID's for each daemon running on your system
          and, if possible, use "chroot" to jail that process away from the
          rest of your system.</para>
        </note>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ensure you have adequate access controls for the
        <filename>$BUGZILLA_HOME/data/</filename> directory, as well as the
        <filename>$BUGZILLA_HOME/localconfig</filename> file.
        The localconfig file stores your "bugs" database account password. 
        In addition, some
        files under <filename>$BUGZILLA_HOME/data/</filename> store sensitive
        information.
        </para>

        <para>Also, beware that some text editors create backup files in the
        current working directory so you need to also secure files like
        <filename>localconfig~</filename>.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>Simply blocking <computeroutput>.*localconfig.*</computeroutput>
          won't work because the QuickSearch feature requires the web browser
          to be able to retrieve <filename>localconfig.js</filename> and
          others may be introduced in the future (see 
          <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=186383">bug
          186383</ulink> for more information.
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>Bugzilla provides default <filename>.htaccess</filename> files
        to protect the most common Apache installations. However, you should
        verify these are adequate according to the site-wide security policy
        of your web server, and ensure that the <filename>.htaccess</filename>
        files are allowed to <quote>override</quote> default permissions set
        in your Apache configuration files. Covering Apache security is beyond
        the scope of this Guide; please consult the Apache documentation for
        details.
        </para>

        <para>If you are using a web server that does not support the
        <filename>.htaccess</filename> control method, 
        <emphasis>you are at risk!</emphasis>

        After installing, check to see if you can view the file
        <filename>localconfig</filename> in your web browser (e.g.: 
        <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/localconfig">
        http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/localconfig</ulink>

        ). If you can read the contents of this file, your web server has
        not secured your bugzilla directory properly and you must fix this
        problem before deploying Bugzilla. If, however, it gives you a
        "Forbidden" error, then it probably respects the .htaccess
        conventions and you are good to go.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When you run checksetup.pl, the script will attempt to modify
        various permissions on files which Bugzilla uses. If you do not have
        a webservergroup set in the <filename>localconfig</filename> file,
        then Bugzilla will have to make certain files world readable and/or
        writable. 
        <emphasis>THIS IS INSECURE!</emphasis>

        . This means that anyone who can get access to your system can do
        whatever they want to your Bugzilla installation.</para>

        <note>
          <para>This also means that if your webserver runs all cgi scripts
          as the same user/group, anyone on the system who can run cgi
          scripts will be able to take control of your Bugzilla
          installation.</para>
        </note>

        <para>On Apache, you can use <filename>.htaccess</filename> files to
        protect access to these directories, as outlined in Bugs 
        <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=57161">
        57161</ulink> and
        <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=186383">
        186383</ulink>

        for the <filename>localconfig</filename> file, and 
        <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=65572">Bug
        65572</ulink>

        for adequate protection in your <filename>data/</filename> directory.
        Also, don't forget about the <filename>template/</filename> and
        <filename>Bugzilla/</filename> directories and to allow access to the
        <filename>data/webdot</filename> directory for the
        <computeroutput>192.20.225.10</computeroutput> IP address if you are
        using webdot from research.att.com.  The easiest way to
        accomplish this is to set <function>$create_htaccess</function> to 1
        in <filename>localconfig</filename>.  However, the information below
        is provided for those that want to know exactly what is created.
        </para>

        <para>Note the instructions which follow are Apache-specific. If you
        use IIS, Netscape, or other non-Apache web servers, please consult
        your system documentation for how to secure these files from being
        transmitted to curious users.</para>

        <para><filename>$BUGZILLA_HOME/.htaccess</filename>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
# don't allow people to retrieve non-cgi executable files or our private data
<FilesMatch ^(.*\.pl|.*localconfig.*|processmail|runtests.sh)$>
  deny from all
</FilesMatch>
<FilesMatch ^(localconfig.js|localconfig.rdf)$>
  allow from all
</FilesMatch>
        ]]></programlisting> 
        </para>

        <para><filename>$BUGZILLA_HOME/data/.htaccess</filename> 
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
# nothing in this directory is retrievable unless overriden by an .htaccess
# in a subdirectory; the only exception is duplicates.rdf, which is used by
# duplicates.xul and must be loadable over the web
deny from all
<Files duplicates.rdf>
  allow from all
</Files>
        ]]></programlisting>
        </para>

        <para><filename>$BUGZILLA_HOME/data/webdot</filename>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
# Restrict access to .dot files to the public webdot server at research.att.com 
# if research.att.com ever changed their IP, or if you use a different
# webdot server, you'll need to edit this
<FilesMatch ^[0-9]+\.dot$>
  Allow from 192.20.225.10
  Deny from all
</FilesMatch>

# Allow access by a local copy of 'dot' to .png, .gif, .jpg, and
# .map files
<FilesMatch ^[0-9]+\.(png|gif|jpg|map)$>
  Allow from all
</FilesMatch>

# And no directory listings, either.
Deny from all
        ]]></programlisting>
        </para>

        <para><filename>$BUGZILLA_HOME/Bugzilla/.htaccess</filename>
        <programlisting>
# nothing in this directory is retrievable unless overriden by an .htaccess
# in a subdirectory
deny from all
         </programlisting>
         </para>

        <para><filename>$BUGZILLA_HOME/template/.htaccess</filename>
        <programlisting>
# nothing in this directory is retrievable unless overriden by an .htaccess
# in a subdirectory
deny from all
         </programlisting>
         </para>

      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="cust-templates">
    <title>Template Customization</title>
    
    <para>
      One of the large changes for 2.16 was the templatization of the
      entire user-facing UI, using the 
      <ulink url="http://www.template-toolkit.org">Template Toolkit</ulink>.
      Administrators can now configure the look and feel of Bugzilla without
      having to edit Perl files or face the nightmare of massive merge
      conflicts when they upgrade to a newer version in the future.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Templatization also makes localized versions of Bugzilla possible, 
      for the first time. In the future, a Bugzilla installation may
      have templates installed for multiple localizations, and select
      which ones to use based on the user's browser language setting.      
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>What to Edit</title>
      <para>
        There are two different ways of editing of Bugzilla's templates,
        and which you use depends mainly on how you upgrade Bugzilla. The
        template directory structure is that there's a top level directory,
        <filename>template</filename>, which contains a directory for
        each installed localization. The default English templates are
        therefore in <filename>en</filename>. Underneath that, there
        is the <filename>default</filename> directory and optionally the 
        <filename>custom</filename> directory. The <filename>default</filename>
        directory contains all the templates shipped with Bugzilla, whereas
        the <filename>custom</filename> directory does not exist at first and
        must be created if you want to use it.
      </para>

      <para>
        The first method of making customizations is to directly edit the
        templates in <filename>template/en/default</filename>. This is
        probably the best method for small changes if you are going to use
        the CVS method of upgrading, because if you then execute a
        <command>cvs update</command>, any template fixes will get
        automagically merged into your modified versions.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you use this method, your installation will break if CVS conflicts
        occur.
      </para>

      <para>
        The other method is to copy the templates into a mirrored directory
        structure under <filename>template/en/custom</filename>.  The templates
        in this directory automatically override those in default.  
        This is the technique you
        need to use if you use the overwriting method of upgrade, because
        otherwise your changes will be lost.  This method is also better if
        you are using the CVS method of upgrading and are going to make major
        changes, because it is guaranteed that the contents of this directory
        will not be touched during an upgrade, and you can then decide whether
        to continue using your own templates, or make the effort to merge your
        changes into the new versions by hand.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you use this method, your installation may break if incompatible
        changes are made to the template interface.  If such changes are made
        they will be documented in the release notes, provided you are using a
        stable release of Bugzilla.  If you use using unstable code, you will
        need to deal with this one yourself, although if possible the changes
        will be mentioned before they occur in the deprecations section of the
        previous stable release's release notes.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          Don't directly edit the compiled templates in 
          <filename class="directory">data/template/*</filename> - your
          changes will be lost when Template Toolkit recompiles them.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>How To Edit Templates</title>
      
     <para>
        The syntax of the Template Toolkit language is beyond the scope of
        this guide. It's reasonably easy to pick up by looking at the current 
        templates; or, you can read the manual, available on the
        <ulink url="http://www.template-toolkit.org">Template Toolkit home
        page</ulink>. However, you should particularly remember (for security
        reasons) to always HTML filter things which come from the database or
        user input, to prevent cross-site scripting attacks.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        However, one thing you should take particular care about is the need
        to properly HTML filter data that has been passed into the template.
        This means that if the data can possibly contain special HTML characters
        such as &lt;, and the data was not intended to be HTML, they need to be
        converted to entity form, ie &amp;lt;.  You use the 'html' filter in the
        Template Toolkit to do this.  If you fail to do this, you may open up
        your installation to cross-site scripting attacks.
      </para>

      <para>
        Also note that Bugzilla adds a few filters of its own, that are not
        in standard Template Toolkit.  In particular, the 'url_quote' filter
        can convert characters that are illegal or have special meaning in URLs,
        such as &amp;, to the encoded form, ie %26.  This actually encodes most
        characters (but not the common ones such as letters and numbers and so
        on), including the HTML-special characters, so there's never a need to
        HTML filter afterwards.
      </para>
 
      <para>
        Editing templates is a good way of doing a "poor man's custom fields".
        For example, if you don't use the Status Whiteboard, but want to have
        a free-form text entry box for "Build Identifier", then you can just
        edit the templates to change the field labels. It's still be called
        status_whiteboard internally, but your users don't need to know that.
      </para>
      
      <note>
        <para>
          If you are making template changes that you intend on submitting back
          for inclusion in standard Bugzilla, you should read the relevant
          sections of the 
          <ulink url="http://www.bugzilla.org/developerguide.html">Developers'
          Guide</ulink>.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>
            
    
    <section>
      <title>Template Formats</title>
      
      <para>
        Some CGIs have the ability to use more than one template. For
        example, buglist.cgi can output bug lists as RDF or two
        different forms of HTML (complex and simple). (Try this out
        by appending <filename>&amp;format=simple</filename> to a buglist.cgi
        URL on your Bugzilla installation.) This
        mechanism, called template 'formats', is extensible.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        To see if a CGI supports multiple output formats, grep the
        CGI for "ValidateOutputFormat". If it's not present, adding
        multiple format support isn't too hard - see how it's done in
        other CGIs.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        To make a new format template for a CGI which supports this, 
        open a current template for
        that CGI and take note of the INTERFACE comment (if present.) This 
        comment defines what variables are passed into this template. If 
        there isn't one, I'm afraid you'll have to read the template and
        the code to find out what information you get. 
      </para>     
  
      <para>
        Write your template in whatever markup or text style is appropriate.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        You now need to decide what content type you want your template
        served as. Open up the <filename>localconfig</filename> file and find the 
        <filename>$contenttypes</filename>
        variable. If your content type is not there, add it. Remember
        the three- or four-letter tag assigned to you content type. 
        This tag will be part of the template filename.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Save the template as <filename>&lt;stubname&gt;-&lt;formatname&gt;.&lt;contenttypetag&gt;.tmpl</filename>. 
        Try out the template by calling the CGI as 
        <filename>&lt;cginame&gt;.cgi?format=&lt;formatname&gt;</filename> .
      </para>       
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <title>Particular Templates</title>
      
      <para>
        There are a few templates you may be particularly interested in
        customizing for your installation.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <command>index.html.tmpl</command>:
        This is the Bugzilla front page.
      </para>      

      <para>
        <command>global/header.html.tmpl</command>:
        This defines the header that goes on all Bugzilla pages.
        The header includes the banner, which is what appears to users
        and is probably what you want to edit instead.  However the
        header also includes the HTML HEAD section, so you could for
        example add a stylesheet or META tag by editing the header.
      </para>

      <para>
        <command>global/banner.html.tmpl</command>:
        This contains the "banner", the part of the header that appears
        at the top of all Bugzilla pages.  The default banner is reasonably
        barren, so you'll probably want to customize this to give your
        installation a distinctive look and feel.  It is recommended you
        preserve the Bugzilla version number in some form so the version 
        you are running can be determined, and users know what docs to read.
      </para>

      <para>
        <command>global/footer.html.tmpl</command>:
        This defines the footer that goes on all Bugzilla pages.  Editing
        this is another way to quickly get a distinctive look and feel for
        your Bugzilla installation.
      </para>

      <para>
        <command>bug/create/user-message.html.tmpl</command>:
        This is a message that appears near the top of the bug reporting page.
        By modifying this, you can tell your users how they should report
        bugs.
      </para>

      <para>
        <command>bug/process/midair.html.tmpl</command>:
        This is the page used if two people submit simultaneous changes to the
        same bug.  The second person to submit their changes will get this page
        to tell them what the first person did, and ask if they wish to
        overwrite those changes or go back and revisit the bug.  The default
        title and header on this page read "Mid-air collision detected!"  If
        you work in the aviation industry, or other environment where this
        might be found offensive (yes, we have true stories of this happening)
        you'll want to change this to something more appropriate for your
        environment.
      </para>
        
      <para>
        <command>bug/create/create.html.tmpl</command> and
        <command>bug/create/comment.txt.tmpl</command>:
        You may wish to get bug submitters to give certain bits of structured
        information, each in a separate input widget, for which there is not a
        field in the database. The bug entry system has been designed in an
        extensible fashion to enable you to define arbitrary fields and widgets,
        and have their values appear formatted in the initial
        Description, rather than in database fields. An example of this
        is the mozilla.org 
        <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/enter_bug.cgi?format=guided">guided 
        bug submission form</ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>
        To make this work, create a custom template for 
        <filename>enter_bug.cgi</filename> (the default template, on which you
        could base it, is <filename>create.html.tmpl</filename>),
        and either call it <filename>create.html.tmpl</filename> or use a format and
        call it <filename>create-&lt;formatname&gt;.html.tmpl</filename>.
        Put it in the <filename class="directory">custom/bug/create</filename>
        directory. In it, add widgets for each piece of information you'd like
        collected - such as a build number, or set of steps to reproduce.
      </para>

      <para>
        Then, create a template like 
        <filename>custom/bug/create/comment.txt.tmpl</filename>, also named
        after your format if you are using one, which
        references the form fields you have created. When a bug report is
        submitted, the initial comment attached to the bug report will be
        formatted according to the layout of this template.
      </para> 

      <para>
        For example, if your enter_bug template had a field
        <programlisting>&lt;input type="text" name="buildid" size="30"&gt;</programlisting>
        and then your comment.txt.tmpl had
        <programlisting>BuildID: [% form.buildid %]</programlisting>
        then
        <programlisting>BuildID: 20020303</programlisting>
        would appear in the initial checkin comment.
      </para>        
    </section>          
    
  </section>

  <section id="cust-change-permissions">
    <title>Change Permission Customization</title>
    
    <warning>
      <para>
        This feature should be considered experimental; the Bugzilla code you
        will be changing is not stable, and could change or move between 
        versions. Be aware that if you make modifications to it, you may have
        to re-make them or port them if Bugzilla changes internally between
        versions.
      </para>
    </warning>
       
    <para>
      Companies often have rules about which employees, or classes of employees,
      are allowed to change certain things in the bug system. For example, 
      only the bug's designated QA Contact may be allowed to VERIFY the bug.
      Bugzilla has been
      designed to make it easy for you to write your own custom rules to define
      who is allowed to make what sorts of value transition.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      For maximum flexibility, customizing this means editing Bugzilla's Perl 
      code. This gives the administrator complete control over exactly who is
      allowed to do what. The relevant function is called 
      <filename>CheckCanChangeField()</filename>,
      and is found in <filename>process_bug.cgi</filename> in your 
      Bugzilla directory. If you open that file and grep for 
      "sub CheckCanChangeField", you'll find it.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      This function has been carefully commented to allow you to see exactly
      how it works, and give you an idea of how to make changes to it. Certain
      marked sections should not be changed - these are the "plumbing" which
      makes the rest of the function work. In between those sections, you'll
      find snippets of code like:
      <programlisting>    # Allow the owner to change anything.
    if ($ownerid eq $whoid) {
        return 1;
    }</programlisting>
      It's fairly obvious what this piece of code does.
    </para>      
      
    <para>
      So, how does one go about changing this function? Well, simple changes
      can be made just be removing pieces - for example, if you wanted to 
      prevent any user adding a comment to a bug, just remove the lines marked
      "Allow anyone to change comments." And if you want the reporter to have
      no special rights on bugs they have filed, just remove the entire section
      which refers to him.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      More complex customizations are not much harder. Basically, you add
      a check in the right place in the function, i.e. after all the variables
      you are using have been set up. So, don't look at $ownerid before 
      $ownerid has been obtained from the database. You can either add a
      positive check, which returns 1 (allow) if certain conditions are true,
      or a negative check, which returns 0 (deny.) E.g.:
      <programlisting>    if ($field eq "qacontact") {
        if (UserInGroup("quality_assurance")) {
            return 1;
        } 
        else {
            return 0;
        }
    }</programlisting>
      This says that only users in the group "quality_assurance" can change
      the QA Contact field of a bug. Getting more weird:
      <programlisting>    if (($field eq "priority") &&
        ($vars->{'user'}{'login'} =~ /.*\@example\.com$/))
    {
        if ($oldvalue eq "P1") {
            return 1;
        } 
        else {
            return 0;
        }
    }</programlisting>
      This says that if the user is trying to change the priority field,
      and their email address is @example.com, they can only do so if the
      old value of the field was "P1". Not very useful, but illustrative.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      For a list of possible field names, look in 
      <filename>data/versioncache</filename> for the list called 
      <filename>@::log_columns</filename>. If you need help writing custom
      rules for your organization, ask in the newsgroup.
    </para>    
  </section>   
  
  <section id="upgrading">
    <title>Upgrading to New Releases</title>

    <para>A plain Bugzilla is fairly easy to upgrade from one version to a
    newer one. Always read the release notes to see if there are any issues
    that you might need to take note of. It is recommended that you take a 
    backup of your database and your entire Bugzilla installation before attempting an
    upgrade. You can upgrade a 'clean' installation by untarring a new
    tarball over the old installation. If you are upgrading from 2.12 or
    later, and have cvs installed, you can type <filename>cvs -z3 update</filename>, 
    and resolve conflicts if there are any.
    </para>
    
    <para>However, things get a bit more complicated if you've made
    changes to Bugzilla's code. In this case, you may have to re-make or
    reapply those changes. One good method is to take a diff of your customized
    version against the original, so you can survey all that you've changed.
    Hopefully, templatization will reduce the need for
    this in the future.</para>

    <para>From version 2.8 onward, Bugzilla databases can be automatically
    carried forward during an upgrade. However, because the developers of
    Bugzilla are constantly adding new
    tables, columns and fields, you'll probably get SQL errors if you just
    update the code and attempt to use Bugzilla. Always run the
    <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> 
    script whenever you upgrade your installation.</para>

    <para>If you are running Bugzilla version 2.8 or lower, and wish to
    upgrade to the latest version, please consult the file,
    "UPGRADING-pre-2.8" in the Bugzilla root directory after untarring the
    archive.</para>
  </section>

  <!-- Integrating Bugzilla with Third-Party Tools -->
  &integration;

</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-auto-insert-required-elements:t
sgml-balanced-tag-edit:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-namecase-general:t
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-parent-document:("Bugzilla-Guide.sgml" "book" "chapter")
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-tag-region-if-active:t
End:
-->

