<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1//EN"> -->
<chapter id="administration">
  <title>Administering Bugzilla</title>

  <section id="parameters">
    <title>Bugzilla Configuration</title>

    <para>Bugzilla is configured by changing various parameters, accessed
    from the "Edit parameters" link in the page footer. Here are
    some of the key parameters on that page. You should run down this
    list and set them appropriately after installing Bugzilla.</para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>checklist</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para> 
        <command>maintainer</command>:
        The maintainer parameter is the email address of the person 
        responsible for maintaining this
        Bugzilla installation. The address need not be that of a valid Bugzilla
        account.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>urlbase</command>:
        This parameter defines the fully qualified domain name and web 
        server path to your Bugzilla installation.</para>

        <para>For example, if your Bugzilla query page is
        <filename>http://www.foo.com/bugzilla/query.cgi</filename>, 
        set your <quote>urlbase</quote>
        to <filename>http://www.foo.com/bugzilla/</filename>.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>makeproductgroups</command>:
        This dictates whether or not to automatically create groups
        when new products are created.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>useentrygroupdefault</command>:
        Bugzilla products can have a group associated with them, so that
        certain users can only see bugs in certain products. When this 
        parameter is set to <quote>on</quote>, this 
        causes the initial group controls on newly created products 
        to place all newly-created bugs in the group 
        having the same name as the product immediately.
        After a product is initially created, the group controls
        can be further adjusted without interference by 
        this mechanism.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>shadowdb</command>:
        You run into an interesting problem when Bugzilla reaches a
        high level of continuous activity. MySQL supports only table-level
        write locking. What this means is that if someone needs to make a
        change to a bug, they will lock the entire table until the operation
        is complete. Locking for write also blocks reads until the write is
        complete. Note that more recent versions of mysql support row level
        locking using different table types. These types are slower than the
        standard type, and Bugzilla does not yet take advantage of features
        such as transactions which would justify this speed decrease. The
        Bugzilla team are, however, happy to hear about any experiences with
        row level locking and Bugzilla.</para>

        <para>The <quote>shadowdb</quote>
        parameter was designed to get around this limitation. While only a
        single user is allowed to write to a table at a time, reads can
        continue unimpeded on a read-only shadow copy of the database.
        Although your database size will double, a shadow database can cause
        an enormous performance improvement when implemented on extremely
        high-traffic Bugzilla databases.</para>
        
        <para>
        As a guide, on reasonably old hardware, mozilla.org began needing 
        <quote>shadowdb</quote>
        when they reached around 40,000 Bugzilla users with several hundred
        Bugzilla bug changes and comments per day.</para>

        <para>The value of the parameter defines the name of the 
        shadow bug database. You will need to set the host and port settings
        from the params page, and set up replication in your database server
        so that updates reach this readonly mirror. Consult your database
        documentation for more detail.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>shutdownhtml</command>:

        If you need to shut down Bugzilla to perform administration, enter
        some descriptive HTML here and anyone who tries to use Bugzilla will
        receive a page to that effect. Obviously, editparams.cgi will
        still be accessible so you can remove the HTML and re-enable Bugzilla.
        :-)
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>passwordmail</command>:

        Every time a user creates an account, the text of
        this parameter (with substitutions) is sent to the new user along with
        their password message.</para>

        <para>Add any text you wish to the "passwordmail" parameter box. For
        instance, many people choose to use this box to give a quick training
        blurb about how to use Bugzilla at your site.</para>
      </step>


      <step>
        <para>
	<command>movebugs</command>:

	This option is an undocumented feature to allow moving bugs
	between separate Bugzilla installations.  You will need to understand
	the source code in order to use this feature.  Please consult
	<filename>movebugs.pl</filename> in your Bugzilla source tree for
	further documentation, such as it is.
	</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>useqacontact</command>:

        This allows you to define an email address for each component, in
        addition
        to that of the default owner, who will be sent carbon copies of
        incoming bugs.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
        <command>usestatuswhiteboard</command>:
        This defines whether you wish to have a free-form, overwritable field
        associated with each bug. The advantage of the Status Whiteboard is
        that it can be deleted or modified with ease, and provides an
        easily-searchable field for indexing some bugs that have some trait
        in common.         
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>whinedays</command>:
        Set this to the number of days you want to let bugs go
        in the NEW or REOPENED state before notifying people they have
        untouched new bugs. If you do not plan to use this feature, simply do
        not set up the whining cron job described in the installation
        instructions, or set this value to "0" (never whine).</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>commenton*</command>:
        All these
        fields allow you to dictate what changes can pass without comment,
        and which must have a comment from the person who changed them.
        Often, administrators will allow users to add themselves to the CC
        list, accept bugs, or change the Status Whiteboard without adding a
        comment as to their reasons for the change, yet require that most
        other changes come with an explanation.</para>

        <para>Set the "commenton" options according to your site policy. It
        is a wise idea to require comments when users resolve, reassign, or
        reopen bugs at the very least. 
        <note>
          <para>It is generally far better to require a developer comment
          when resolving bugs than not. Few things are more annoying to bug
          database users than having a developer mark a bug "fixed" without
          any comment as to what the fix was (or even that it was truly
          fixed!)</para>
        </note>
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>
        <command>supportwatchers</command>:

        Turning on this option allows users to ask to receive copies of 
        all a particular other user's bug email. This is, of
        course, subject to the groupset restrictions on the bug; if the 
        <quote>watcher</quote>
        would not normally be allowed to view a bug, the watcher cannot get
        around the system by setting herself up to watch the bugs of someone
        with bugs outside her privileges. They would still only receive email
        updates for those bugs she could normally view.</para>        
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>

  <section id="useradmin">
    <title>User Administration</title>

    <section id="defaultuser">
      <title>Creating the Default User</title>

      <para>When you first run checksetup.pl after installing Bugzilla, it
      will prompt you for the administrative username (email address) and
      password for this "super user". If for some reason you delete
      the "super user" account, re-running checksetup.pl will again prompt
      you for this username and password.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>If you wish to add more administrative users, add them to 
        the "admin" group and, optionally, add edit the tweakparams, editusers,
        creategroups, editcomponents, and editkeywords groups to add the
        entire admin group to those groups.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section id="manageusers">
      <title>Managing Other Users</title>

      <section id="createnewusers">
        <title>Creating new users</title>

        <para>Your users can create their own user accounts by clicking the
        "New Account" link at the bottom of each page (assuming they
        aren't logged in as someone else already.) However, should you
        desire to create user accounts ahead of time, here is how you do
        it.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>After logging in, click the "Users" link at the footer of
            the query page, and then click "Add a new user".</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Fill out the form presented. This page is self-explanatory.
            When done, click "Submit".</para>

            <note>
              <para>Adding a user this way will 
              <emphasis>not</emphasis>

              send an email informing them of their username and password.
              While useful for creating dummy accounts (watchers which
              shuttle mail to another system, for instance, or email
              addresses which are a mailing list), in general it is
              preferable to log out and use the 
              <quote>New Account</quote>

              button to create users, as it will pre-populate all the
              required fields and also notify the user of her account name
              and password.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="modifyusers">
        <title>Modifying Users</title>

        <para>To see a specific user, search for their login name
        in the box provided on the "Edit Users" page. To see all users, 
        leave the box blank.</para>

        <para>You can search in different ways the listbox to the right
        of the text entry box. You can match by 
        case-insensitive substring (the default),
        regular expression, or a 
        <emphasis>reverse</emphasis>
        regular expression match, which finds every user name which does NOT
        match the regular expression. (Please see
        the <command>man regexp</command>
        manual page for details on regular expression syntax.)
        </para>

        <para>Once you have found your user, you can change the following
        fields:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>Login Name</emphasis>: 
            This is generally the user's full email address. However, if you
            have are using the emailsuffix Param, this may just be the user's
            login name. Note that users can now change their login names
            themselves (to any valid email address.)
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>Real Name</emphasis>: The user's real name. Note that
            Bugzilla does not require this to create an account.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>Password</emphasis>: 
            You can change the user's password here. Users can automatically
            request a new password, so you shouldn't need to do this often.
            If you want to disable an account, see Disable Text below.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>Disable Text</emphasis>: 
            If you type anything in this box, including just a space, the
            user is prevented from logging in, or making any changes to 
            bugs via the web interface. 
            The HTML you type in this box is presented to the user when
            they attempt to perform these actions, and should explain
            why the account was disabled.
            <warning>
              <para>Don't disable all the administrator accounts!</para>
            </warning>

            <note>
              <para>The user can still submit bugs via
              the e-mail gateway, if you set it up, even if the disabled text
              field is filled in. The e-mail gateway should 
              <emphasis>not</emphasis>
              be enabled for secure installations of Bugzilla.</para>
            </note>
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>&lt;groupname&gt;</emphasis>: 
            If you have created some groups, e.g. "securitysensitive", then
            checkboxes will appear here to allow you to add users to, or
            remove them from, these groups.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>canconfirm</emphasis>: 
            This field is only used if you have enabled the "unconfirmed"
            status. If you enable this for a user,
            that user can then move bugs from "Unconfirmed" to a "Confirmed"
            status (e.g.: "New" status).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>creategroups</emphasis>: 
            This option will allow a user to create and destroy groups in
            Bugzilla.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>editbugs</emphasis>: 
            Unless a user has this bit set, they can only edit those bugs
            for which they are the assignee or the reporter. Even if this
            option is unchecked, users can still add comments to bugs.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>editcomponents</emphasis>: 
            This flag allows a user to create new products and components,
            as well as modify and destroy those that have no bugs associated
            with them. If a product or component has bugs associated with it,
            those bugs must be moved to a different product or component
            before Bugzilla will allow them to be destroyed.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>editkeywords</emphasis>: 
            If you use Bugzilla's keyword functionality, enabling this
            feature allows a user to create and destroy keywords. As always,
            the keywords for existing bugs containing the keyword the user
            wishes to destroy must be changed before Bugzilla will allow it
            to die.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>editusers</emphasis>: 
            This flag allows a user to do what you're doing right now: edit
            other users. This will allow those with the right to do so to
            remove administrator privileges from other users or grant them to
            themselves. Enable with care.</para>
          </listitem>


          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>tweakparams</emphasis>: 
            This flag allows a user to change Bugzilla's Params 
            (using <filename>editparams.cgi</filename>.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>
            <emphasis>&lt;productname&gt;</emphasis>: 
            This allows an administrator to specify the products in which 
            a user can see bugs. The user must still have the 
            "editbugs" privilege to edit bugs in these products.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="products">
    <title>Products</title>

    <para>
    <glossterm linkend="gloss-product" baseform="product">
    Products</glossterm>

    are the broadest category in Bugzilla, and tend to represent real-world
    shipping products. E.g. if your company makes computer games, 
    you should have one product per game, perhaps a "Common" product for 
    units of technology used in multiple games, and maybe a few special
     products (Website, Administration...)</para>

    <para>Many of Bugzilla's settings are configurable on a per-product
    basis. The number of "votes" available to users is set per-product, 
    as is the number of votes
    required to move a bug automatically from the UNCONFIRMED status to the
    NEW status.</para>

    <para>To create a new product:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select "products" from the footer</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "Add" link in the bottom right</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enter the name of the product and a description. The
        Description field may contain HTML.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Don't worry about the "Closed for bug entry", "Maximum Votes
    per person", "Maximum votes a person can put on a single bug",
    "Number of votes a bug in this Product needs to automatically get out
    of the UNCOMFIRMED state", and "Version" options yet. We'll cover
    those in a few moments.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="components">
    <title>Components</title>

    <para>Components are subsections of a Product. E.g. the computer game 
    you are designing may have a "UI"
    component, an "API" component, a "Sound System" component, and a
    "Plugins" component, each overseen by a different programmer. It
    often makes sense to divide Components in Bugzilla according to the
    natural divisions of responsibility within your Product or
    company.</para>

    <para>
    Each component has a owner and (if you turned it on in the parameters),
    a QA Contact. The owner should be the primary person who fixes bugs in
    that component. The QA Contact should be the person who will ensure
    these bugs are completely fixed. The Owner, QA Contact, and Reporter
    will get email when new bugs are created in this Component and when
    these bugs change. Default Owner and Default QA Contact fields only
    dictate the 
    <emphasis>default assignments</emphasis>; 
    these can be changed on bug submission, or at any later point in
    a bug's life.</para>

    <para>To create a new Component:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "Edit components" link from the "Edit product"
        page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "Add" link in the bottom right.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fill out the "Component" field, a short "Description", 
        the "Initial Owner" and "Initial QA Contact" (if enabled.) 
        The Component and Description fields may contain HTML; 
        the "Initial Owner" field must be a login name
        already existing in the database. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="versions">
    <title>Versions</title>

    <para>Versions are the revisions of the product, such as "Flinders
    3.1", "Flinders 95", and "Flinders 2000". Version is not a multi-select
    field; the usual practice is to select the earliest version known to have
    the bug.
    </para>

    <para>To create and edit Versions:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the "Edit product" screen, select "Edit Versions"</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You will notice that the product already has the default
        version "undefined". Click the "Add" link in the bottom right.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enter the name of the Version. This field takes text only. 
        Then click the "Add" button.</para>
      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="milestones">
    <title>Milestones</title>

    <para>Milestones are "targets" that you plan to get a bug fixed by. For
    example, you have a bug that you plan to fix for your 3.0 release, it
    would be assigned the milestone of 3.0.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Milestone options will only appear for a Product if you turned
      on the "usetargetmilestone" Param in the "Edit Parameters" screen.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>To create new Milestones, set Default Milestones, and set
    Milestone URL:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select "Edit milestones" from the "Edit product" page.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select "Add" in the bottom right corner.
        text</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enter the name of the Milestone in the "Milestone" field. You
        can optionally set the "sortkey", which is a positive or negative
        number (-255 to 255) that defines where in the list this particular
        milestone appears. This is because milestones often do not 
        occur in alphanumeric order For example, "Future" might be
        after "Release 1.2". Select "Add".</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>From the Edit product screen, you can enter the URL of a 
        page which gives information about your milestones and what
        they mean. </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section id="voting">
    <title>Voting</title>

    <para>Voting allows users to be given a pot of votes which they can allocate
    to bugs, to indicate that they'd like them fixed. 
    This allows developers to gauge
    user need for a particular enhancement or bugfix. By allowing bugs with
    a certain number of votes to automatically move from "UNCONFIRMED" to
    "NEW", users of the bug system can help high-priority bugs garner
    attention so they don't sit for a long time awaiting triage.</para>

    <para>To modify Voting settings:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Navigate to the "Edit product" screen for the Product you
        wish to modify</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Maximum Votes per person</emphasis>:
        Setting this field to "0" disables voting.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Maximum Votes a person can put on a single
         bug</emphasis>: 
         It should probably be some number lower than the
        "Maximum votes per person". Don't set this field to "0" if
        "Maximum votes per person" is non-zero; that doesn't make
        any sense.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Number of votes a bug in this product needs to
        automatically get out of the UNCONFIRMED state</emphasis>: 
        Setting this field to "0" disables the automatic move of
        bugs from UNCONFIRMED to NEW. 
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Once you have adjusted the values to your preference, click
        "Update".</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="quips">
    <title>Quips</title>

    <para>
      Quips are small text messages that can be configured to appear
      next to search results. A Bugzilla installation can have its own specific
      quips. Whenever a quip needs to be displayed, a random selection
      is made from the pool of already existing quips.
    </para>
  
    <para>
      Quips are controlled by the <emphasis>enablequips</emphasis> parameter.
      It has several possible values: on, approved, frozen or off.
      In order to enable quips approval you need to set this parameter
      to "approved". In this way, users are free to submit quips for
      addition but an administrator must explicitly approve them before
      they are actually used.
    </para>

    <para>
      In order to see the user interface for the quips, it is enough to click
      on a quip when it is displayed together with the search results. Or
      it can be seen directly in the browser by visiting the quips.cgi URL
      (prefixed with the usual web location of the Bugzilla installation).
      Once the quip interface is displayed, it is enough to click the
      "view and edit the whole quip list" in order to see the administration
      page. A page with all the quips available in the database will
      be displayed.
    </para>

    <para>
      Next to each tip there is a checkbox, under the
      "Approved" column. Quips who have this checkbox checked are
      already approved and will appear next to the search results.
      The ones that have it unchecked are still preserved in the
      database but they will not appear on search results pages.
      User submitted quips have initially the checkbox unchecked.
    </para>
  
    <para>
      Also, there is a delete link next to each quip,
      which can be used in order to permanently delete a quip.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="groups">
    <title>Groups and Group Security</title>

    <para>Groups allow the administrator
    to isolate bugs or products that should only be seen by certain people.
    The association between products and groups is controlled from
    the product edit page under <quote>Edit Group Controls.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
    If the makeproductgroups param is on, a new group will be automatically
    created for every new product. It is primarily available for backward
    compatibility with older sites. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that group permissions are such that you need to be a member
      of <emphasis>all</emphasis> the groups a bug is in, for whatever
      reason, to see that bug. Similarly, you must be a member 
      of <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the entry groups for a product 
      to add bugs to a product and you must be a member 
      of <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the canedit groups for a product
      in order to make <emphasis>any</emphasis> change to bugs in that
      product.
    </para>    
    <section>
      <title>Creating Groups</title>
      <para>To create Groups:</para>
  
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the <quote>groups</quote>
          link in the footer.</para>
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem>
          <para>Take a moment to understand the instructions on the <quote>Edit
          Groups</quote> screen, then select the <quote>Add Group</quote> link.</para>
        </listitem>
  
        <listitem>
          <para>Fill out the <quote>Group</quote>, <quote>Description</quote>, 
           and <quote>User RegExp</quote> fields. 
           <quote>User RegExp</quote> allows you to automatically
           place all users who fulfill the Regular Expression into the new group. 
           When you have finished, click <quote>Add</quote>.</para>
           <para>Users whose email addresses match the regular expression
           will automatically be members of the group as long as their 
           email addresses continue to match the regular expression.</para>
           <note>
             <para>This is a change from 2.16 where the regular expression
             resulted in a user acquiring permanent membership in a group.
             To remove a user from a group the user was in due to a regular
             expression in version 2.16 or earlier, the user must be explicitly
             removed from the group.</para>
           </note>
           <warning>
             <para>If specifying a domain in the regexp, make sure you end
             the regexp with a $. Otherwise, when granting access to 
             "@mycompany\.com", you will allow access to 
             'badperson@mycompany.com.cracker.net'. You need to use 
             '@mycompany\.com$' as the regexp.</para>
           </warning>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you plan to use this group to directly control
          access to bugs, check the "use for bugs" box. Groups
          not used for bugs are still useful because other groups
          can include the group as a whole.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>After you add your new group, edit the new group.  On the
          edit page, you can specify other groups that should be included
          in this group and which groups should be permitted to add and delete
          users from this group.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
  
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Assigning Users to Groups</title>
      <para>Users can become a member of a group in several ways.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The user can be explicitly placed in the group by editing
          the user's own profile</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The group can include another group of which the user is
          a member.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The user's email address can match a regular expression
          that the group specifies to automatically grant membership to
          the group.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Assigning Group Controls to Products</title>
      <para>
      On the product edit page, there is a page to edit the 
      <quote>Group Controls</quote> 
      for a product. This  allows you to 
      configure how a group relates to the product. 
      Groups may be applicable, default, 
      and mandatory as well as used to control entry 
      or used to make bugs in the product
      totally read-only unless the group restrictions are met. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
      For each group, it is possible to specify if membership in that
      group is...
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          required for bug entry, 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Not applicable to this product(NA),
          a possible restriction for a member of the 
          group to place on a bug in this product(Shown),
          a default restriction for a member of the 
          group to place on a bug in this product(Default),
          or a mandatory restriction to be placed on bugs 
          in this product(Mandatory).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Not applicable by non-members to this product(NA),
          a possible restriction for a non-member of the 
          group to place on a bug in this product(Shown),
          a default restriction for a non-member of the 
          group to place on a bug in this product(Default),
          or a mandatory restriction to be placed on bugs 
          in this product when entered by a non-member(Mandatory).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          required in order to make <emphasis>any</emphasis> change
          to bugs in this product <emphasis>including comments.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>These controls are often described in this order, so a 
      product that requires a user to be a member of group "foo" 
      to enter a bug and then requires that the bug stay resticted
      to group "foo" at all times and that only members of group "foo"
      can edit the bug even if they otherwise could see the bug would 
      have its controls summarized by...</para>
      <programlisting> 
foo: ENTRY, MANDATORY/MANDATORY, CANEDIT
      </programlisting>
      
    </section>
    <section>
    <title>Common Applications of Group Controls</title>
      <section>
      <title>General User Access With Security Group</title>
      <para>To permit any user to file bugs in each product (A, B, C...) 
      and to permit any user to submit those bugs into a security
      group....</para>
      <programlisting> 
Product A...
security: SHOWN/SHOWN
Product B...
security: SHOWN/SHOWN
Product C...
security: SHOWN/SHOWN
      </programlisting>
      </section>
      <section>
      <title>General User Access With A Security Product</title>
      <para>To permit any user to file bugs in a Security product
      while keeping those bugs from becoming visible to anyone
      outside the securityworkers group unless a member of the
      securityworkers group removes that restriction....</para>
      <programlisting> 
Product Security...
securityworkers: DEFAULT/MANDATORY
      </programlisting>
      </section>
      <section>
      <title>Product Isolation With Common Group</title>
      <para>To permit users of product A to access the bugs for
      product A, users of product B to access product B, and support
      staff to access both, 3 groups are needed</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Support: Contains members of the support staff.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>AccessA: Contains users of product A and the Support group.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>AccessB: Contains users of product B and the Support group.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>Once these 3 groups are defined, the products group controls
      can be set to..</para>
      <programlisting>
Product A...
AccessA: ENTRY, MANDATORY/MANDATORY
Product B...
AccessB: ENTRY, MANDATORY/MANDATORY
      </programlisting>
      <para>Optionally, the support group could be permitted to make
      bugs inaccessible to the users and could be permitted to publish
      bugs relevant to all users in a common product that is read-only
      to anyone outside the support group. That configuration could
      be...</para>
      <programlisting>
Product A...
AccessA: ENTRY, MANDATORY/MANDATORY
Support: SHOWN/NA
Product B...
AccessB: ENTRY, MANDATORY/MANDATORY
Support: SHOWN/NA
Product Common...
Support: ENTRY, DEFAULT/MANDATORY, CANEDIT
      </programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="upgrading">
    <title>Upgrading to New Releases</title>

    <warning>
      <para>Upgrading is a one-way process. You should backup your database
      and current Bugzilla directory before attempting the upgrade. If you wish
      to revert to the old Bugzilla version for any reason, you will have to
      restore from these backups.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para>Upgrading Bugzilla is something we all want to do from time to time,
    be it to get new features or pick up the latest security fix. How easy
    it is to update depends on a few factors.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the new version is a revision or a new point release</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How many, if any, local changes have been made</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>There are also three different methods to upgrade your installation.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Using CVS (<xref linkend="upgrade-cvs"/>)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Downloading a new tarball (<xref linkend="upgrade-tarball"/>)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Applying the relevant patches (<xref linkend="upgrade-patches"/>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Which options are available to you may depend on how large a jump
    you are making and/or your network configuration.
    </para>

    <para>Revisions are normally released to fix security vulnerabilities
    and are distinguished by an increase in the third number. For example,
    when 2.16.2 was released, it was a revision to 2.16.1.
    </para>

    <para>Point releases are normally released when the Bugzilla team feels
    that there has been a significant amount of progress made between the
    last point release and the current time. These are often proceeded by a
    stabilization period and release candidates, however the use of 
    development versions or release candidates is beyond the scope of this
    document. Point releases can be distinguished by an increase in the
    second number, or minor version. For example, 2.16.2 is a newer point
    release than 2.14.5.
    </para>

    <para>The examples in this section are written as if you were updating
    to version 2.16.2.  The procedures are the same regardless if you are
    updating to a new point release or a new revision.  However, the chance
    of running into trouble increases when upgrading to a new point release,
    escpecially if you've made local changes.
    </para>

    <para>These examples also assume that your Bugzilla installation is at
    <filename>/var/www/html/bugzilla</filename>. If that is not the case,
    simply substitute the proper paths where appropriate.
    </para>

    <example id="upgrade-cvs">
      <title>Upgrading using CVS</title>

      <para>Every release of Bugzilla, whether it is a revision or a point
      release, is tagged in CVS.  Also, every tarball we have distributed
      since version 2.12 has been primed for using CVS. This does, however,
      require that you are able to access cvs-mirror.mozilla.org on port
      2401.

        <tip>
          <para>If you can do this, updating using CVS is probably the most
          painless method, especially if you have a lot of local changes.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </para>

      <programlisting>
bash$ <command>cd /var/www/html/bugzilla</command>
bash$ <command>cvs login</command>
Logging in to :pserver:anonymous@cvs-mirror.mozilla.org:2401/cvsroot
CVS password: <command>anonymous</command>
bash$ <command>cvs -q update -r BUGZILLA-2_16_2 -dP</command>
P checksetup.pl
P collectstats.pl
P globals.pl
P docs/rel_notes.txt
P template/en/default/list/quips.html.tmpl
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        <caution>
          <para>If a line in the output from <command>cvs update</command>
          begins with a <computeroutput>C</computeroutput> that represents a
          file with local changes that CVS was unable to properly merge. You
          need to resolve these conflicts manually before Bugzilla (or at
          least the portion using that file) will be usable.
          </para>
        </caution>

        <note>
          <para>You also need to run <command>./checksetup.pl</command>
          before your Bugzilla upgrade will be complete.
          </para>
        </note>
      </para>
    </example>

    <example id="upgrade-tarball">
      <title>Upgrading using the tarball</title>

      <para>If you are unable or unwilling to use CVS, another option that's
      always available is to download the latest tarball. This is the most
      difficult option to use, especially if you have local changes.
      </para>

      <programlisting>
bash$ <command>cd /var/www/html</command>
bash$ <command>wget ftp://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/webtools/bugzilla-2.16.2.tar.gz</command>
<emphasis>Output omitted</emphasis>
bash$ <command>tar xzvf bugzilla-2.16.2.tar.gz</command>
bugzilla-2.16.2/
bugzilla-2.16.2/.cvsignore
bugzilla-2.16.2/1x1.gif
<emphasis>Output truncated</emphasis>
bash$ <command>cd bugzilla-2.16.2</command>
bash$ <command>cp ../bugzilla/localconfig* .</command>
bash$ <command>cp -r ../bugzilla/data .</command>
bash$ <command>cd ..</command>
bash$ <command>mv bugzilla bugzilla.old</command>
bash$ <command>mv bugzilla-2.16.2 bugzilla</command>
bash$ <command>cd bugzilla</command>
bash$ <command>./checksetup.pl</command>
<emphasis>Output omitted</emphasis>
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        <warning>
          <para>The <command>cp</command> commands both end with periods which
          is a very important detail, it tells the shell that the destination
          directory is the current working directory. Also, the period at the
          beginning of the <command>./checksetup.pl</command> is important and
          can not be omitted.
          </para>
        </warning>

        <note>
          <para>You will now have to reapply any changes you have made to your
          local installation manually.
          </para>
        </note>
      </para>
    </example>

    <example id="upgrade-patches">
      <title>Upgrading using patches</title>

      <para>The Bugzilla team will normally make a patch file available for
      revisions to go from the most recent revision to the new one. You could
      also read the release notes and grab the patches attached to the
      mentioned bug, but it is safer to use the released patch file as
      sometimes patches get changed before they get checked in. 
      It is also theoretically possible to
      scour the fixed bug list and pick and choose which patches to apply
      from a point release, but this is not recommended either as what you'll
      end up with is a hodge podge Bugzilla that isn't really any version.
      This would also make it more difficult to upgrade in the future.
      </para>

      <programlisting>
bash$ <command>cd /var/www/html/bugzilla</command>
bash$ <command>wget ftp://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/webtools/bugzilla-2.16.1-to-2.16.2.diff.gz</command>
<emphasis>Output omitted</emphasis>
bash$ <command>gunzip bugzilla-2.16.1-to-2.16.2.diff.gz</command>
bash$ <command>patch -p1 &lt; bugzilla-2.16.1-to-2.16.2.diff</command>
patching file checksetup.pl
patching file collectstats.pl
patching file globals.pl
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        <caution>
          <para>If you do this, beware that this doesn't change the entires in
          your <filename id="dir">CVS</filename> directory so it may make
          updates using CVS (<xref linkend="upgrade-cvs"/>) more difficult in the
          future.
          </para>
        </caution>
      </para>
    </example>

  </section>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-auto-insert-required-elements:t
sgml-balanced-tag-edit:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-namecase-general:t
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-parent-document:("Bugzilla-Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-tag-region-if-active:t
End:
-->

