<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"> -->
<chapter id="installation" xreflabel="Bugzilla Installation">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <section id="stepbystep" xreflabel="Bugzilla Installation Step-by-step">
    <title>Step-by-step Install</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>Bugzilla has been successfully installed under Solaris, Linux,
      and Win32. Win32 is not yet officially supported, but many people
      have got it working fine.
      Please see the 
      <xref linkend="win32" />
      for further advice on getting Bugzilla to work on Microsoft
      Windows.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Package List</title>

      <note>
        <para> If you are running the very most recent
        version of Perl and MySQL (both the executables and development
        libraries) on your system, you can skip these manual installation 
        steps for the Perl modules by using Bundle::Bugzilla; see
        <xref linkend="bundlebugzilla" />.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>The software packages necessary for the proper running of
      Bugzilla (with download links) are: 
      <orderedlist>
      
      
<listitem>
  <para>
    <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL database server</ulink>
    (3.22.5 or greater)
  </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
  <para>
    <ulink url="http://www.perl.org">Perl</ulink>
    (5.005 or greater, 5.6.1 is recommended if you wish to
    use Bundle::Bugzilla)
  </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
  <para>Perl Modules (minimum version):
  <orderedlist>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.template-toolkit.org">Template</ulink>
        (v2.07)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.perldoc.com/perl5.6/lib/File/Temp.html">
	File::Temp</ulink> (v1.804) (Prerequisite for Template)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org/modules/by-module/AppConfig/">AppConfig 
        </ulink>
        (v1.52)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org/authors/id/MUIR/modules/Text-Tabs%2BWrap-2001.0131.tar.gz">Text::Wrap</ulink> 
        (v2001.0131)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://search.cpan.org/search?dist=File-Spec">File::Spec 
        </ulink>
        (v0.8.2)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org/modules/by-module/Data/">Data::Dumper 
        </ulink> 
        (any)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org/modules/by-module/Mysql/">DBD::mysql
        </ulink> 
        (v1.2209)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org/modules/by-module/DBI/">DBI</ulink> 
        (v1.13)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org/modules/by-module/Date/">Date::Parse
        </ulink> 
        (any)
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        CGI::Carp 
        (any)
      </para>
    </listitem>

  </orderedlist>
  and, optionally:
  <orderedlist>  
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org/modules/by-module/GD/">GD</ulink>
        (v1.19) for bug charting
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org/modules/by-module/Chart/">Chart::Base 
        </ulink>
        (v0.99c) for bug charting
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        XML::Parser 
        (any) for the XML interface
      </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>
        MIME::Parser 
        (any) for the email interface
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>          
  </para>
</listitem>


<listitem>
  <para>
    The web server of your choice. 
    <ulink url="http://www.apache.org/">Apache</ulink> 
    is highly recommended.
  </para>
</listitem>


      </orderedlist>

      <warning>
        <para>It is a good idea, while installing Bugzilla, to ensure that there
        is some kind of firewall between you and the rest of the Internet,
        because your machine may be insecure for periods during the install.
        Many
        installation steps require an active Internet connection to complete,
        but you must take care to ensure that at no point is your machine
        vulnerable to an attack.</para>
      </warning>

      <note>
        <para>Linux-Mandrake 8.0 includes every
        required and optional library for Bugzilla. The easiest way to
        install them is by using the 
        <filename>urpmi</filename>

        utility. If you follow these commands, you should have everything you
        need for Bugzilla, and 
        <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>

        should not complain about any missing libraries. You may already have
        some of these installed.</para>

        <simplelist>
          <member>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>urpmi perl-mysql</command>
          </member>

          <member>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>urpmi perl-chart</command>
          </member>

          <member>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>urpmi perl-gd</command>
          </member>

          <member>
          <prompt>bash#</prompt>

          <command>urpmi perl-MailTools</command>

          (for Bugzilla email integration)</member>

          <member>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>urpmi apache-modules</command>
          </member>
        </simplelist>
      </note>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="install-mysql">
      <title>MySQL</title>

      <para>Visit the MySQL homepage at 
      <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com">www.mysql.com</ulink>
      to grab and install the latest stable release of the server. 
      </para>
      
      <note>
        <para> Many of the binary
        versions of MySQL store their data files in 
        <filename>/var</filename>.
        On some Unix systems, this is part of a smaller root partition,
        and may not have room for your bug database. You can set the data
         directory as an option to <filename>configure</filename>
         if you build MySQL from source yourself.</para>
      </note>

      <para>If you install from something other than an RPM or Debian 
      package, you will need to add <filename>mysqld</filename>
      to your init scripts so the server daemon will come back up whenever
      your machine reboots. Further discussion of UNIX init sequences are
      beyond the scope of this guide. 
      </para>

      <para>Change your init script to start 
      <filename>mysqld</filename>
      with the ability to accept large packets. By default, 
      <filename>mysqld</filename>
      only accepts packets up to 64K long. This limits the size of
      attachments you may put on bugs. If you add 
      <option>-O max_allowed_packet=1M</option>
      to the command that starts 
      <filename>mysqld</filename>
      (or <filename>safe_mysqld</filename>), 
      then you will be able to have attachments up to about 1 megabyte.
      There is a Bugzilla parameter for maximum attachment size;
      you should configure it to match the value you choose here.</para>

      <para>If you plan on running Bugzilla and MySQL on the same machine,
      consider using the 
      <option>--skip-networking</option>
      option in the init script. This enhances security by preventing
      network access to MySQL.</para>
        
    </section>

    <section id="install-perl">
      <title>Perl</title>

      <para>Any machine that doesn't have Perl on it is a sad machine indeed.
      Perl can be got in source form from 
      <ulink url="http://www.perl.com">perl.com</ulink> for the rare 
      *nix systems which don't have it. 
      Although Bugzilla runs with all post-5.005
      versions of Perl, it's a good idea to be up to the very latest version
      if you can when running Bugzilla. As of this writing, that is Perl
      version &perl-ver;.</para>

      <tip id="bundlebugzilla"
      xreflabel="Using Bundle::Bugzilla instead of manually installing Perl modules">

        <para>You can skip the following Perl module installation steps by
        installing 
        <productname>Bundle::Bugzilla</productname>

        from 
        <glossterm linkend="gloss-cpan">CPAN</glossterm>, 
        which installs all required modules for you.</para>

        <para>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>perl -MCPAN -e 'install "Bundle::Bugzilla"'</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </para>

        <para>Bundle::Bugzilla doesn't include GD, Chart::Base, or
        MIME::Parser, which are not essential to a basic Bugzilla install. If
        installing this bundle fails, you should install each module
        individually to isolate the problem.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section id="perl-modules">
      <title>Perl Modules</title>
      
    <para> 
      All Perl modules can be found on the
      <ulink url="http://www.cpan.org">Comprehensive Perl 
      Archive Network</ulink> (CPAN). The
      CPAN servers have a real tendency to bog down, so please use mirrors.
    </para>
    
      <para>Quality, general Perl module installation instructions can be
      found on the CPAN website, but the easy thing to do is to just use the
      CPAN shell which does all the hard work for you.
      To use the CPAN shell to install a module: 
      </para>

      <para>
        <computeroutput>
          <prompt>bash#</prompt>
          <command>perl -MCPAN -e 'install "&lt;modulename&gt;"'</command>
        </computeroutput>
      </para>
      
      <para>
      To do it the hard way: 
      </para>
      
      <para>Untar the module tarball -- it should create its own
      directory</para>

      <para>CD to the directory just created, and enter the following
      commands: 
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <computeroutput>
              <prompt>bash#</prompt>

              <command>perl Makefile.PL</command>
            </computeroutput>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <computeroutput>
              <prompt>bash#</prompt>

              <command>make</command>
            </computeroutput>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <computeroutput>
              <prompt>bash#</prompt>

              <command>make test</command>
            </computeroutput>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <computeroutput>
              <prompt>bash#</prompt>

              <command>make install</command>
            </computeroutput>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </para>
      
      <warning>
        <para>Many people complain that Perl modules will not install for
        them. Most times, the error messages complain that they are missing a
        file in 
        <quote>@INC</quote>. 
        Virtually every time, this error is due to permissions being set too
        restrictively for you to compile Perl modules or not having the
        necessary Perl development libraries installed on your system.
        Consult your local UNIX systems administrator for help solving these
        permissions issues; if you 
        <emphasis>are</emphasis>
        the local UNIX sysadmin, please consult the newsgroup/mailing list
        for further assistance or hire someone to help you out.</para>
      </warning>


    <section>
      <title>DBI</title>
        
      <para>The DBI module is a generic Perl module used the
      MySQL-related modules. As long as your Perl installation was done
      correctly the DBI module should be a breeze. It's a mixed Perl/C
      module, but Perl's MakeMaker system simplifies the C compilation
      greatly.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Data::Dumper</title>

      <para>The Data::Dumper module provides data structure persistence for
      Perl (similar to Java's serialization). It comes with later
      sub-releases of Perl 5.004, but a re-installation just to be sure it's
      available won't hurt anything.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MySQL-related modules</title>

      <para>The Perl/MySQL interface requires a few mutually-dependent Perl
      modules. These modules are grouped together into the the
      Msql-Mysql-modules package.</para> 

      <para>The MakeMaker process will ask you a few questions about the
      desired compilation target and your MySQL installation. For most of the
      questions the provided default will be adequate, but when asked if your
      desired target is the MySQL or mSQL packages, you should
      select the MySQL related ones. Later you will be asked if you wish to
      provide backwards compatibility with the older MySQL packages; you
      should answer YES to this question. The default is NO.</para>

      <para>A host of 'localhost' should be fine and a testing user of 'test'
      with a null password should find itself with sufficient access to run
      tests on the 'test' database which MySQL created upon installation.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>TimeDate modules</title>

      <para>Many of the more common date/time/calendar related Perl modules
      have been grouped into a bundle similar to the MySQL modules bundle.
      This bundle is stored on the CPAN under the name TimeDate. 
      The component module we're most interested in is the Date::Format
      module, but installing all of them is probably a good idea anyway.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>GD (optional)</title>

      <para>The GD library was written by Thomas Boutell a long while ago to
      programatically generate images in C. Since then it's become the
      defacto standard for programatic image construction. The Perl bindings
      to it found in the GD library are used on millions of web pages to
      generate graphs on the fly. That's what Bugzilla will be using it for
      so you must install it if you want any of the graphing to work.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The Perl GD library requires some other libraries that may or
        may not be installed on your system, including 
        <classname>libpng</classname>
        and 
        <classname>libgd</classname>. 
        The full requirements are listed in the Perl GD library README.
        If compiling GD fails, it's probably because you're
        missing a required library.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Chart::Base (optional)</title>

      <para>The Chart module provides Bugzilla with on-the-fly charting
      abilities. It can be installed in the usual fashion after it has been
      fetched from CPAN. 
      Note that earlier versions that 0.99c used GIFs, which are no longer
      supported by the latest versions of GD.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Template Toolkit</title>

      <para>When you install Template Toolkit, you'll get asked various
      questions about features to enable. The defaults are fine, except
      that it is recommended you use the high speed XS Stash of the Template
      Toolkit, in order to achieve best performance.  However, there are
      known problems with XS Stash and Perl 5.005_02 and lower.  If you
      wish to use these older versions of Perl, please use the regular
      stash.</para>
    </section> 

    
  </section>
  
    <section>
      <title>HTTP Server</title>

      <para>You have a freedom of choice here - Apache, Netscape or any other
      server on UNIX would do. You can run the web server on a
      different machine than MySQL, but need to adjust the MySQL 
      <quote>bugs</quote>
      user permissions accordingly. 
      <note>
        <para>We strongly recommend Apache as the web server to use. The
        Bugzilla Guide installation instructions, in general, assume you are
        using Apache. If you have got Bugzilla working using another webserver,
        please share your experiences with us.</para>
      </note>
      </para>

      <para>You'll want to make sure that your web server will <emphasis>run</emphasis>
      any file
      with the .cgi extension as a CGI program and not simply display the source
      code. If you're
      using Apache that means uncommenting the following line in the httpd.conf
      file: 
      <programlisting>
AddHandler cgi-script .cgi
      </programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>With Apache you'll also want to make sure that within the
      httpd.conf file these lines: 
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
Options +ExecCGI 
AllowOverride Limit
]]></programlisting>

      are in the stanza that covers the directories into which you intend to
      put the bugzilla .html and .cgi files.

        <note>
          <para>AllowOverride Limit allows the use of a Deny statement in the
          .htaccess file generated by checksetup.pl</para>

          <para>Users of older versions of Apache may find the above lines 
          in the srm.conf and access.conf files, respectively.</para>
        </note>
      </para>
      
      <warning>
        <para>There are important files and directories that should not be a
        served by the HTTP server - most files in the 
        <quote>data</quote>
        and 
        <quote>shadow</quote>
        directories and the 
        <quote>localconfig</quote>
        file. You should configure your HTTP server to not serve 
        these files. Failure to do so will expose critical passwords and
        other data. Please see 
        <xref linkend="htaccess" />
        for details on how to do this for Apache; the checksetup.pl
        script should create appropriate .htaccess files for you.</para>
      </warning>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bugzilla</title>

      <para>You should untar the Bugzilla files into a directory that you're
      willing to make writable by the default web server user (probably 
      <quote>nobody</quote>). 
      You may decide to put the files in the main web space for your
      web server or perhaps in 
      <filename>/usr/local</filename>
      with a symbolic link in the web space that points to the Bugzilla
      directory.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>If you symlink the bugzilla directory into your Apache's HTML
        heirarchy, you may receive 
        <errorname>Forbidden</errorname>
        errors unless you add the 
        <quote>FollowSymLinks</quote>
        directive to the &lt;Directory&gt; entry for the HTML root
        in httpd.conf.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>Once all the files are in a web accessible directory, make that
      directory writable by your webserver's user. This is a temporary step
      until you run the post-install 
      <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>
      script, which locks down your installation.</para>

      <para>Lastly, you'll need to set up a symbolic link to 
      <filename>/usr/bonsaitools/bin/perl</filename>
      for the correct location of your Perl executable (probably 
      <filename>/usr/bin/perl</filename>). 
      Otherwise you must hack all the .cgi files to change where they look
      for Perl. This can be done using the following Perl one-liner, but 
      I suggest using the symlink approach to avoid upgrade hassles.
      </para>
      
      <para> 
        <programlisting>
perl -pi -e 's@#\!/usr/bonsaitools/bin/perl@#\!/usr/bin/perl@' *cgi *pl Bug.pm processmail syncshadowdb
        </programlisting>

        Change <filename>/usr/bin/perl</filename> to match the location
        of Perl on your machine.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting Up the MySQL Database</title>

      <para>After you've gotten all the software installed and working you're
      ready to start preparing the database for its life as the back end to
      a high quality bug tracker.</para>

      <para>First, you'll want to fix MySQL permissions to allow access from
      Bugzilla. For the purpose of this Installation section, the Bugzilla
      username will be 
      <quote>bugs</quote>, and will have minimal permissions. 
      </para>

      <para>Begin by giving the MySQL root user a password. MySQL passwords are limited
      to 16 characters. 
      <simplelist>
        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>mysql -u root mysql</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>

        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

            <command>UPDATE user SET Password=PASSWORD('&lt;new_password'&gt;)
            WHERE user='root';</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>

        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

            <command>FLUSH PRIVILEGES;</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>
      </simplelist>

      From this point on, if you need to access MySQL as the MySQL root user,
      you will need to use 
      <command>mysql -u root -p</command>

      and enter &lt;new_password&gt;. Remember that MySQL user names have
      nothing to do with Unix user names (login names).</para>

      <para>Next, we use an SQL <command>GRANT</command> command to create a 
      <quote>bugs</quote>

      user, and grant sufficient permissions for checksetup.pl, which we'll
      use later, to work its magic. This also restricts the 
      <quote>bugs</quote>
      user to operations within a database called 
      <quote>bugs</quote>, and only allows the account to connect from 
      <quote>localhost</quote>. 
      Modify it to reflect your setup if you will be connecting from
      another machine or as a different user.</para>

      <para>Remember to set &lt;bugs_password&gt; to some unique password. 
      <simplelist>
        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

            <command>GRANT SELECT,INSERT,UPDATE,DELETE,INDEX,
            ALTER,CREATE,DROP,REFERENCES ON bugs.* TO bugs@localhost
            IDENTIFIED BY '&lt;bugs_password&gt;';</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>

        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

            <command>FLUSH PRIVILEGES;</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title> 
      <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>
      </title>

      <para>Next, run the magic checksetup.pl script. (Many thanks to 
      <ulink url="mailto:holgerschurig@nikocity.de">Holger Schurig </ulink> 
      for writing this script!) 
      This script is designed to make sure your MySQL database and other
      configuration options are consistent with the Bugzilla CGI files. 
      It will make sure Bugzilla files and directories have reasonable
      permissions, set up the 
      <filename>data</filename>
      directory, and create all the MySQL tables. 
      <simplelist>
        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>./checksetup.pl</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>
      </simplelist>

      The first time you run it, it will create a file called 
      <filename>localconfig</filename>.</para>
      
      <para>This file contains a variety of settings you may need to tweak
      including how Bugzilla should connect to the MySQL database.</para>

      <para>The connection settings include: 
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>server's host: just use 
          <quote>localhost</quote>
          if the MySQL server is local</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>database name: 
          <quote>bugs</quote>
          if you're following these directions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL username: 
          <quote>bugs</quote>
          if you're following these directions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Password for the 
          <quote>bugs</quote>
          MySQL account; (&lt;bugs_password&gt;) above</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </para>

      <para>Once you are happy with the settings, 
      <filename>su</filename> to the user
      your web server runs as, and re-run 
      <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>. (Note: on some security-conscious
      systems, you may need to change the login shell for the webserver 
      account before you can do this.)
      On this second run, it will create the database and an administrator
      account for which you will be prompted to provide information.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The checksetup.pl script is designed so that you can run it at
        any time without causing harm. You should run it after any upgrade to
        Bugzilla.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Securing MySQL</title>

      <para>If you followed the installation instructions for setting up your
      "bugs" and "root" user in MySQL, much of this should not apply to you.
      If you are upgrading an existing installation of Bugzilla, you should
      pay close attention to this section.</para>

      <para>Most MySQL installs have "interesting" default security
      parameters: 
      <simplelist>
        <member>mysqld defaults to running as root</member>

        <member>it defaults to allowing external network connections</member>

        <member>it has a known port number, and is easy to detect</member>

        <member>it defaults to no passwords whatsoever</member>

        <member>it defaults to allowing "File_Priv"</member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <para>This means anyone from anywhere on the internet can not only drop
      the database with one SQL command, and they can write as root to the
      system.</para>

      <para>To see your permissions do: 
      <simplelist>
        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>mysql -u root -p</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>

        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

            <command>use mysql;</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>

        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

            <command>show tables;</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>

        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

            <command>select * from user;</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>

        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

            <command>select * from db;</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <para>To fix the gaping holes: 
      <simplelist>
        <member>DELETE FROM user WHERE User='';</member>

        <member>UPDATE user SET Password=PASSWORD('new_password') WHERE
        user='root';</member>

        <member>FLUSH PRIVILEGES;</member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <para>If you're not running "mit-pthreads" you can use: 
      <simplelist>
        <member>GRANT USAGE ON *.* TO bugs@localhost;</member>

        <member>GRANT ALL ON bugs.* TO bugs@localhost;</member>

        <member>REVOKE DROP ON bugs.* FROM bugs@localhost;</member>

        <member>FLUSH PRIVILEGES;</member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <para>With "mit-pthreads" you'll need to modify the "globals.pl"
      Mysql-&gt;Connect line to specify a specific host name instead of
      "localhost", and accept external connections: 
      <simplelist>
        <member>GRANT USAGE ON *.* TO bugs@bounce.hop.com;</member>

        <member>GRANT ALL ON bugs.* TO bugs@bounce.hop.com;</member>

        <member>REVOKE DROP ON bugs.* FROM bugs@bounce.hop.com;</member>

        <member>FLUSH PRIVILEGES;</member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <para>Consider also: 
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Turning off external networking with "--skip-networking",
          unless you have "mit-pthreads", in which case you can't. Without
          networking, MySQL connects with a Unix domain socket.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>using the --user= option to mysqld to run it as an
          unprivileged user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>running MySQL in a chroot jail</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>running the httpd in a chroot jail</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>making sure the MySQL passwords are different from the OS
          passwords (MySQL "root" has nothing to do with system
          "root").</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>running MySQL on a separate untrusted machine</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>making backups ;-)</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Configuring Bugzilla</title>
      <para>
      You should run through the parameters on the Edit Parameters page
      (link in the footer) and set them all to appropriate values. 
      They key parameters are documented in <xref linkend="parameters" />.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="extraconfig">
    <title>Optional Additional Configuration</title>

    <section>
      <title>Dependency Charts</title>

      <para>As well as the text-based dependency graphs, Bugzilla also
      supports dependency graphing, using a package called 'dot'.
      Exactly how this works is controlled by the 'webdotbase' parameter,
      which can have one of three values:
      </para>

      <para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            A complete file path to the command 'dot' (part of 
            <ulink url="http://www.graphviz.org/">GraphViz</ulink>) 
            will generate the graphs locally
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            A URL prefix pointing to an installation of the webdot package will
            generate the graphs remotely
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            A blank value will disable dependency graphing.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>So, to get this working, install
      <ulink url="http://www.graphviz.org/">GraphViz</ulink>. If you
      do that, you need to
      <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/mod/mod_imap.html">enable
      server-side image maps</ulink> in Apache.
      Alternatively, you could set up a webdot server, or use the AT&amp;T 
      public webdot server (the
      default for the webdotbase param). Note that AT&amp;T's server won't work
      if Bugzilla is only accessible using HTTPS.
      </para>
   </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bug Graphs</title>

      <para>As long as you installed the GD and Graph::Base Perl modules you
      might as well turn on the nifty Bugzilla bug reporting graphs.</para>

      <para>Add a cron entry like this to run 
      <filename>collectstats.pl</filename> 
      daily at 5 after midnight: 
      <simplelist>
        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>bash#</prompt>

            <command>crontab -e</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>

        <member>
          <computeroutput>5 0 * * * cd &lt;your-bugzilla-directory&gt; ;
          ./collectstats.pl</computeroutput>
        </member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <para>After two days have passed you'll be able to view bug graphs from
      the Bug Reports page.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Whining Cron</title>

      <para>By now you have a fully functional Bugzilla, but what good are
      bugs if they're not annoying? To help make those bugs more annoying you
      can set up Bugzilla's automatic whining system to complain at engineers
      which leave their bugs in the NEW state without triaging them.
      </para>
      <para>
      This can be done by
      adding the following command as a daily crontab entry (for help on that
      see that crontab man page): 
      <simplelist>
        <member>
          <computeroutput>
            <command>cd &lt;your-bugzilla-directory&gt; ;
            ./whineatnews.pl</command>
          </computeroutput>
        </member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <tip>
        <para>Depending on your system, crontab may have several manpages.
        The following command should lead you to the most useful page for
        this purpose: 
        <programlisting>
man 5 crontab
	</programlisting>
        </para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section id="bzldap">
      <title>LDAP Authentication</title>
      <para>
        <warning>
          <para>This information on using the LDAP
            authentication options with Bugzilla is old, and the authors do
            not know of anyone who has tested it. Approach with caution.
          </para>
        </warning>
      </para>
      
      <para>
      The existing authentication
      scheme for Bugzilla uses email addresses as the primary user ID, and a
      password to authenticate that user. All places within Bugzilla where
      you need to deal with user ID (e.g assigning a bug) use the email
      address. The LDAP authentication builds on top of this scheme, rather
      than replacing it. The initial log in is done with a username and
      password for the LDAP directory. This then fetches the email address
      from LDAP and authenticates seamlessly in the standard Bugzilla
      authentication scheme using this email address. If an account for this
      address already exists in your Bugzilla system, it will log in to that
      account. If no account for that email address exists, one is created at
      the time of login. (In this case, Bugzilla will attempt to use the
      "displayName" or "cn" attribute to determine the user's full name.)
      After authentication, all other user-related tasks are still handled by
      email address, not LDAP username. You still assign bugs by email
      address, query on users by email address, etc.
      </para>
      
      <para>Using LDAP for Bugzilla authentication requires the 
      Mozilla::LDAP (aka PerLDAP) Perl module. The
      Mozilla::LDAP module in turn requires Netscape's Directory SDK for C.
      After you have installed the SDK, then install the PerLDAP module.
      Mozilla::LDAP and the Directory SDK for C are both 
      <ulink url="http://www.mozilla.org/directory/">available for
      download</ulink> from mozilla.org. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
      Set the Param 'useLDAP' to "On" **only** if you will be using an LDAP
      directory for
      authentication. Be very careful when setting up this parameter; if you
      set LDAP authentication, but do not have a valid LDAP directory set up,
      you will not be able to log back in to Bugzilla once you log out. (If
      this happens, you can get back in by manually editing the data/params
      file, and setting useLDAP back to 0.)
      </para>
      
      <para>If using LDAP, you must set the
      three additional parameters: Set LDAPserver to the name (and optionally
      port) of your LDAP server. If no port is specified, it defaults to the
      default port of 389. (e.g "ldap.mycompany.com" or
      "ldap.mycompany.com:1234") Set LDAPBaseDN to the base DN for searching
      for users in your LDAP directory. (e.g. "ou=People,o=MyCompany") uids
      must be unique under the DN specified here. Set LDAPmailattribute to
      the name of the attribute in your LDAP directory which contains the
      primary email address. On most directory servers available, this is
      "mail", but you may need to change this.
      </para>      

      <para>You can also try using <ulink url="http://www.openldap.org/">
      OpenLDAP</ulink> with Bugzilla, using any of a number of administration
      tools.  You should apply the patch attached this bug:
      <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=158630">
      http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=158630</ulink>, then set
      the following object classes for your users:

      <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>objectClass: person</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>objectClass: organizationalPerson</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>objectClass: inetOrgPerson</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>objectClass: top</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>objectClass: posixAccount</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>objectClass: shadowAccount</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      Please note that this patch <emphasis>has not</emphasis> yet been
      accepted by the Bugzilla team, and so you may need to do some
      manual tweaking.  That said, it looks like Net::LDAP is probably
      the way to go in the future.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="content-type"
    xreflabel="Preventing untrusted Bugzilla content from executing malicious Javascript code">

      <title>Preventing untrusted Bugzilla content from executing malicious
      Javascript code</title>

      <para>It is possible for a Bugzilla to execute malicious Javascript
      code. Due to internationalization concerns, we are unable to
      incorporate the code changes necessary to fulfill the CERT advisory
      requirements mentioned in 
      <ulink
      url="http://www.cet.org/tech_tips/malicious_code_mitigation.html/#3">
      http://www.cet.org/tech_tips/malicious_code_mitigation.html/#3</ulink>.
      Executing the following code snippet from a UNIX command shell will
      rectify the problem if your Bugzilla installation is intended for an
      English-speaking audience. As always, be sure your Bugzilla
      installation has a good backup before making changes, and I recommend
      you understand what the script is doing before executing it.</para>

      <para>
        <programlisting>
bash# perl -pi -e "s/Content-Type\: text\/html/Content-Type\: text\/html\; charset=ISO-8859-1/i" *.cgi *.pl
        </programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>All this one-liner command does is search for all instances of 
      <quote>Content-type: text/html</quote>

      and replaces it with 
      <quote>Content-Type: text/html; charset=ISO-8859-1</quote>

      . This specification prevents possible Javascript attacks on the
      browser, and is suggested for all English-speaking sites. For
      non-English-speaking Bugzilla sites, I suggest changing 
      <quote>ISO-8859-1</quote>, above, to 
      <quote>UTF-8</quote>.</para>
      
      <para>Note: using &lt;meta&gt; tags to set the charset is not
      recommended, as there's a bug in Netscape 4.x which causes pages
      marked up in this way to load twice.</para>
    </section>    
    
    <section id="htaccess" xreflabel=".htaccess files and security">
      <title>
      <filename>.htaccess</filename>
      files and security</title>

      <para>To enhance the security of your Bugzilla installation, Bugzilla's
      <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> script will generate 
      <glossterm>
        <filename>.htaccess</filename>
      </glossterm>

      files which the Apache webserver can use to restrict access to the
      bugzilla data files. 
      These .htaccess files will not work with Apache 1.2.x - but this
      has security holes, so you shouldn't be using it anyway. 
      <note>
        <para>If you are using an alternate provider of 
        <productname>webdot</productname>

        services for graphing (as described when viewing 
        <filename>editparams.cgi</filename>

        in your web browser), you will need to change the ip address in 
        <filename>data/webdot/.htaccess</filename>

        to the ip address of the webdot server that you are using.</para>
      </note>
      </para>

      <para>The default .htaccess file may not provide adequate access
      restrictions, depending on your web server configuration. Be sure to
      check the &lt;Directory&gt; entries for your Bugzilla directory so that
      the 
      <filename>.htaccess</filename>

      file is allowed to override web server defaults. For instance, let's
      assume your installation of Bugzilla is installed to 
      <filename>/usr/local/bugzilla</filename>

      . You should have this &lt;Directory&gt; entry in your 
      <filename>httpd.conf</filename>

      file:</para>

      <para>
      
<programlisting><![CDATA[
<Directory /usr/local/bugzilla/>
  Options +FollowSymLinks +Indexes +Includes +ExecCGI
  AllowOverride All
</Directory>
]]></programlisting>

      </para>

      <para>The important part above is 
      <quote>AllowOverride All</quote>

      . Without that, the 
      <filename>.htaccess</filename>

      file created by 
      <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>

      will not have sufficient permissions to protect your Bugzilla
      installation.</para>

      <para>If you are using Internet Information Server (IIS) or another 
      web server which does not observe 
      <filename>.htaccess</filename>
      conventions, you can disable their creation by editing 
      <filename>localconfig</filename>
      and setting the 
      <varname>$create_htaccess</varname>
      variable to 
      <parameter>0</parameter>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="directoryindex" xreflabel="Modifying the Apache
    DirectoryIndex parameter to use index.cgi">
      <title>
        <filename>directoryindex</filename> for the Bugzilla default page.
      </title>
      
      <para>You should modify the &lt;DirectoryIndex&gt; parameter for
      the Apache virtual host running your Bugzilla installation to
      allow <filename>index.cgi</filename> as the index page for a
      directory, as well as the usual <filename>index.html</filename>,
      <filename>index.htm</filename>, and so forth. </para>
    </section>

    <section id="mod-throttle"
    xreflabel="Using mod_throttle to prevent Denial of Service attacks">
      <title>
      <filename>mod_throttle</filename>

      and Security</title>

      <para>It is possible for a user, by mistake or on purpose, to access
      the database many times in a row which can result in very slow access
      speeds for other users. If your Bugzilla installation is experiencing
      this problem , you may install the Apache module 
      <filename>mod_throttle</filename>

      which can limit connections by ip-address. You may download this module
      at 
      <ulink url="http://www.snert.com/Software/Throttle/">
      http://www.snert.com/Software/Throttle/</ulink>. 
      Follow the instructions to install into your Apache install. 
      <emphasis>This module only functions with the Apache web
      server!</emphasis>
      You may use the 
      <command>ThrottleClientIP</command>

      command provided by this module to accomplish this goal. See the 
      <ulink url="http://www.snert.com/Software/Throttle/">Module
      Instructions</ulink>
      for more information.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="win32" xreflabel="Win32 Installation Notes">
    <title>Win32 Installation Notes</title>

    <para>This section covers installation on Microsoft Windows. 
    Bugzilla has been made to work on Win32 platforms, but the Bugzilla team
    wish to emphasise that The easiest way to install Bugzilla on
    Intel-archiecture machines
    is to install some variant of GNU/Linux, then follow the UNIX
    installation instructions in this Guide. If you have any influence in the
    platform choice for running this system, please choose GNU/Linux instead
    of Microsoft Windows.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>After that warning, here's the situation for 2.16
      and Windows. It doesn't work at all out of the box. 
      You are almost certainly better off getting
      the 2.17 version from CVS (after consultation with the Bugzilla Team to
      make sure you are pulling on a stable day) because we'll be doing a load
      of work to make the Win32 experience more pleasant than it is now.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para>
    If you still want to try this, to have any hope of getting it to work,
    you'll need to apply the 
    <ulink url="">mail patch</ulink> from 
    <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=124174">bug 124174</ulink>.
    After that, you'll need to read the (outdated) installation 
    instructions below, some (probably a lot better) <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/attachment.cgi?id=84430&amp;action=view">more
     recent ones</ulink> kindly provided by Toms Baugis and Jean-Sebastien 
     Guay, and also check the 
     <ulink url="http://www.bugzilla.org/releases/2.16/docs/win32.html">Bugzilla 2.16 Win32 update page
     </ulink>. If we get time,
     we'll write some better installation instructions for 2.16 and put
     them up there. But no promises.
    </para>
    
    <section id="wininstall" xreflabel="Win32 Installation: Step-by-step">
      <title>Win32 Installation: Step-by-step</title>

      <note>
        <para>You should be familiar with, and cross-reference, the rest of
        the 
        <xref linkend="installation" />

        section while performing your Win32 installation.</para>

        <para>Making Bugzilla work on Microsoft Windows is no picnic. Support
        for Win32 has improved dramatically in the last few releases, but, if
        you choose to proceed, you should be a 
        <emphasis>very</emphasis>

        skilled Windows Systems Administrator with strong troubleshooting
        abilities, a high tolerance for pain, and moderate perl skills.
        Bugzilla on NT requires hacking source code and implementing some
        advanced utilities. What follows is the recommended installation
        procedure for Win32; additional suggestions are provided in 
        <xref linkend="faq" />

        .</para>
      </note>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Install 
          <ulink url="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Web Server</ulink>

          for Windows, and copy the Bugzilla files somewhere Apache can serve
          them. Please follow all the instructions referenced in 
          <xref linkend="installation" />

          regarding your Apache configuration, particularly instructions
          regarding the 
          <quote>AddHandler</quote>

          parameter and 
          <quote>ExecCGI</quote>

          .</para>

          <note>
            <para>You may also use Internet Information Server or Personal
            Web Server for this purpose. However, setup is quite different.
            If ActivePerl doesn't seem to handle your file associations
            correctly (for .cgi and .pl files), please consult 
            <xref linkend="faq" />

            .</para>

            <para>If you are going to use IIS, if on Windows NT you must be
            updated to at least Service Pack 4. Windows 2000 ships with a
            sufficient version of IIS.</para>
          </note>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Install 
          <ulink url="http://www.activestate.com/">ActivePerl</ulink>

          for Windows. Check 
          <ulink
          url="http://aspn.activestate.com/ASPN/Downloads/ActivePerl/">
          http://aspn.activestate.com/ASPN/Downloads/ActivePerl</ulink>

          for a current compiled binary.</para>

          <para>Please also check the following links to fully understand the
          status of ActivePerl on Win32: 
          <ulink url="http://language.perl.com/newdocs/pod/perlport.html">
          Perl Porting</ulink>

          , and 
          <ulink
          url="http://ftp.univie.ac.at/packages/perl/ports/nt/FAQ/perlwin32faq5.html">
          Perl on Win32 FAQ</ulink>
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Use ppm from your perl\bin directory to install the following
          packs: DBI, DBD-Mysql, TimeDate, Chart, Date-Calc, Date-Manip, GD,
          AppConfig, and Template. You may need to extract them from .zip
          format using Winzip or other unzip program first. Most of these
          additional ppm modules can be downloaded from ActiveState, but
          AppConfig and Template should be obtained from OpenInteract using 
          <ulink type="http" url="http://openinteract.sourceforge.net/">the
          instructions on the Template Toolkit web site</ulink>

          .</para>

          <note>
            <para>You can find a list of modules at 
            <ulink
            url="http://www.activestate.com/PPMPackages/zips/5xx-builds-only">
            http://www.activestate.com/PPMPackages/zips/5xx-builds-only/</ulink>

            or 
            <ulink url="http://www.activestate.com/PPMPackages/5.6plus">
            http://www.activestate.com/PPMPackages/5.6plus</ulink>
            </para>
          </note>

          <para>The syntax for ppm is: 
          <computeroutput>
            <prompt>C:&gt;</prompt>

            <command>ppm &lt;modulename&gt;</command>
          </computeroutput>
          </para>

          <example>
            <title>Installing ActivePerl ppd Modules on Microsoft
            Windows</title>

            <para>
              <prompt>C:&gt;</prompt>

              <command>ppm 
              <option>DBD-Mysql</option>
              </command>
            </para>

            <para>Watch your capitalization!</para>
          </example>

          <para>ActiveState's 5.6Plus directory also contains an AppConfig
          ppm, so you might see the following error when trying to install
          the version at OpenInteract:</para>

          <para>
            <computeroutput>Error installing package 'AppConfig': Read a PPD
            for 'AppConfig', but it is not intended for this build of Perl
            (MSWin32-x86-multi-thread)</computeroutput>
          </para>

          <para>If so, download both 
          <ulink
          url="http://openinteract.sourceforge.net/ppmpackages/AppConfig.tar.gz">
          the tarball</ulink>

          and 
          <ulink
          url="http://openinteract.sourceforge.net/ppmpackages/AppConfig.ppd">
          the ppd</ulink>

          directly from OpenInteract, then run ppm from within the same
          directory to which you downloaded those files and install the
          package by referencing the ppd file explicitly via in the install
          command, f.e.: 
          <example>
            <title>Installing OpenInteract ppd Modules manually on Microsoft
            Windows</title>

            <para>
              <computeroutput>
                <command>install 
                <filename>C:\AppConfig.ppd</filename>
                </command>
              </computeroutput>
            </para>
          </example>
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Install MySQL for NT. 
          <note>
            <para>You can download MySQL for Windows NT from 
            <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL.com</ulink>

            . Some find it helpful to use the WinMySqlAdmin utility, included
            with the download, to set up the database.</para>
          </note>
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Setup MySQL</para>

          <substeps>
            <step>
              <para>
                <computeroutput>
                  <prompt>C:&gt;</prompt>

                  <command>C:\mysql\bin\mysql -u root mysql</command>
                </computeroutput>
              </para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>
                <computeroutput>
                  <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

                  <command>DELETE FROM user WHERE Host='localhost' AND
                  User='';</command>
                </computeroutput>
              </para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>
                <computeroutput>
                  <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

                  <command>UPDATE user SET Password=PASSWORD ('new_password')
                  WHERE user='root';</command>
                </computeroutput>
              </para>

              <para>
              <quote>new_password</quote>

              , above, indicates whatever password you wish to use for your 
              <quote>root</quote>

              user.</para>
            </step>

            <step id="ntbugs-password">
              <para>
                <computeroutput>
                  <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

                  <command>GRANT SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE, INDEX,
                  ALTER, CREATE, DROP, REFERENCES ON bugs.* to bugs@localhost
                  IDENTIFIED BY 'bugs_password';</command>
                </computeroutput>
              </para>

              <para>
              <quote>bugs_password</quote>

              , above, indicates whatever password you wish to use for your 
              <quote>bugs</quote>

              user.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>
                <computeroutput>
                  <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

                  <command>FLUSH PRIVILEGES;</command>
                </computeroutput>
              </para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>
                <computeroutput>
                  <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

                  <command>create database bugs;</command>
                </computeroutput>
              </para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>
                <computeroutput>
                  <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt>

                  <command>exit;</command>
                </computeroutput>
              </para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>
                <computeroutput>
                  <prompt>C:&gt;</prompt>

                  <command>C:\mysql\bin\mysqladmin -u root -p
                  reload</command>
                </computeroutput>
              </para>
            </step>
          </substeps>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Edit 
          <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>

          in your Bugzilla directory. Change this line:</para>

          <para>
            <programlisting>my $webservergid =
            getgrnam($my_webservergroup);</programlisting>
          </para>

          <para>to</para>

          <para>
          <programlisting>my $webservergid =
          $my_webservergroup;</programlisting>

          or the name of the group you wish to own the files explicitly: 
          <programlisting>my $webservergid =
          'Administrators'</programlisting>
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Run 
          <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>

          from the Bugzilla directory.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Edit 
          <filename>localconfig</filename>

          to suit your requirements. Set 
          <varname>$db_pass</varname>

          to your 
          <quote>bugs_password</quote>

          from 
          <xref linkend="ntbugs-password" />

          , and 
          <varname>$webservergroup</varname>

          to 
          <quote>8</quote>

          .</para>

          <note>
            <para>Not sure on the 
            <quote>8</quote>

            for 
            <varname>$webservergroup</varname>

            above. If it's wrong, please send corrections.</para>
          </note>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Edit 
          <filename>defparams.pl</filename>

          to suit your requirements. Particularly, set 
          <varname>DefParam("maintainer")</varname>

          and 
          <varname>DefParam("urlbase") to match your install.</varname>
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>This is yet another step I'm not sure of, since the
            maintainer of this documentation does not maintain Bugzilla on
            NT. If you can confirm or deny that this step is required, please
            let me know.</para>
          </note>
        </step>

        <step>
          <note>
            <para>There are several alternatives to Sendmail that will work
            on Win32. The one mentioned here is a 
            <emphasis>suggestion</emphasis>

            , not a requirement. Some other mail packages that can work
            include 
            <ulink url="http://www.blat.net/">BLAT</ulink>

            , 
            <ulink url="http://www.geocel.com/windmail/">Windmail</ulink>

            , 
            <ulink url="http://www.dynamicstate.com/">Mercury
            Sendmail</ulink>

            , and the CPAN Net::SMTP Perl module (available in .ppm). Every
            option requires some hacking of the Perl scripts for Bugzilla to
            make it work. The option here simply requires the least.</para>
          </note>

          <procedure>
            <step>
              <para>Download NTsendmail, available from
              <ulink url="http://www.ntsendmail.com/">
              www.ntsendmail.com</ulink>

              . You must have a "real" mail server which allows you to relay
              off it in your $ENV{"NTsendmail"} (which you should probably
              place in globals.pl)</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Put ntsendmail.pm into your .\perl\lib directory.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Add to globals.pl:</para>

              <programlisting># these settings configure the NTsendmail
              process use NTsendmail;
              $ENV{"NTsendmail"}="your.smtpserver.box";
              $ENV{"NTsendmail_debug"}=1;
              $ENV{"NTsendmail_max_tries"}=5;</programlisting>

              <note>
                <para>Some mention to also edit 
                <varname>$db_pass</varname>

                in 
                <filename>globals.pl</filename>

                to be your 
                <quote>bugs_password</quote>

                . Although this may get you around some problem
                authenticating to your database, since globals.pl is not
                normally restricted by 
                <filename>.htaccess</filename>

                , your database password is exposed to whoever uses your web
                server.</para>
              </note>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para>Find and comment out all occurences of 
              <quote>
                <command>open(SENDMAIL</command>
              </quote>

              in your Bugzilla directory. Then replace them with: 
              <programlisting># new sendmail functionality my $mail=new
              NTsendmail; my $from="bugzilla\@your.machine.name.tld"; my
              $to=$login; my $subject=$urlbase;
              $mail-&gt;send($from,$to,$subject,$msg);</programlisting>
              </para>

              <note>
                <para>Some have found success using the commercial product, 
                <productname>Windmail</productname>

                . You could try replacing your sendmail calls with: 
                <programlisting>open SENDMAIL,
                "|\"C:/General/Web/tools/Windmail 4.0 Beta/windmail\" -t &gt;
                mail.log";</programlisting>

                or something to that effect.</para>
              </note>
            </step>
          </procedure>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Change all references in all files from 
          <filename>processmail</filename>

          to 
          <filename>processmail.pl</filename>

          , and rename 
          <filename>processmail</filename>

          to 
          <filename>processmail.pl</filename>

          .</para>

          <note>
            <para>Many think this may be a change we want to make for
            main-tree Bugzilla. It's painless for the UNIX folks, and will
            make the Win32 people happier.</para>
          </note>

          <note>
            <para>Some people have suggested using the Net::SMTP Perl module
            instead of NTsendmail or the other options listed here. You can
            change processmail.pl to make this work. 
            <programlisting>
<![CDATA[

my $smtp = Net::SMTP->new('<Name of your SMTP server>');   #connect to SMTP server
$smtp->mail('<your name>@<you smpt server>');# use the sender's adress here
$smtp->to($tolist); # recipient's address
$smtp->data();  # Start the mail
$smtp->datasend($msg);
$smtp->dataend();   # Finish sending the mail
$smtp->quit;    # Close the SMTP connection
$logstr = "$logstr; mail sent to $tolist $cclist";
}

]]>
            </programlisting>

            here is a test mail program for Net::SMTP: 
            <programlisting>
<![CDATA[

use Net::SMTP;
 my $smtp = Net::SMTP->new('<Name of your SMTP server', Timeout => 30, Debug
=> 1, ); # connect to SMTP server
                 $smtp->auth;
                $smtp->mail('you@yourcompany.com');# use the sender's adress
here
                $smtp->to('someotherAddress@someotherdomain.com'); #
recipient's address
                $smtp->data();  # Start the mail
                $smtp->datasend('test');
                $smtp->dataend();   # Finish sending the mail
                $smtp->quit;    # Close the SMTP connection
exit;

]]>
            </programlisting>
            </para>
          </note>
        </step>

        <step>
          <note>
            <para>This step is optional if you are using IIS or another web
            server which only decides on an interpreter based upon the file
            extension (.pl), rather than the 
            <quote>shebang</quote>

            line (#/usr/bonsaitools/bin/perl)</para>
          </note>

          <para>Modify the path to perl on the first line (#!) of all files
          to point to your Perl installation, and add 
          <quote>perl</quote>

          to the beginning of all Perl system calls that use a perl script as
          an argument. This may take you a while. There is a 
          <quote>setperl.csh</quote>

          utility to speed part of this procedure, available in the 
          <xref linkend="patches" />

          section of The Bugzilla Guide. However, it requires the Cygwin
          GNU-compatible environment for Win32 be set up in order to work.
          See 
          <ulink url="http://www.cygwin.com/">http://www.cygwin.com/</ulink>

          for details on obtaining Cygwin.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Modify the invocation of all system() calls in all perl
          scripts in your Bugzilla directory. You should specify the full
          path to perl for each system() call. For instance, change this line
          in processmail: 
          <programlisting>
<![CDATA[ 
system ("./processmail",@ARGLIST); 
        </programlisting> to
        <programlisting> 
system ("C:\\perl\\bin\\perl", "processmail", @ARGLIST);
]]>
          </programlisting>
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Add 
          <function>binmode()</function>

          calls so attachments will work (
          <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=62000">bug
          62000</ulink>

          ).</para>

          <para>Because Microsoft Windows based systems handle binary files
          different than Unix based systems, you need to add the following
          lines to 
          <filename>createattachment.cgi</filename>

          and 
          <filename>showattachment.cgi</filename>

          before the 
          <function>require 'CGI.pl';</function>

          line.</para>

          <para>
            <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
binmode(STDIN);
binmode(STDOUT);
]]>
            </programlisting>
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>According to 
            <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=62000">
            bug 62000</ulink>

            , the perl documentation says that you should always use 
            <function>binmode()</function>

            when dealing with binary files, but never when dealing with text
            files. That seems to suggest that rather than arbitrarily putting
            
            <function>binmode()</function>

            at the beginning of the attachment files, there should be logic
            to determine if 
            <function>binmode()</function>

            is needed or not.</para>
          </note>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <tip>
        <para>If you are using IIS or Personal Web Server, you must add cgi
        relationships to Properties -&gt; Home directory (tab) -&gt;
        Application Settings (section) -&gt; Configuration (button), such
        as:</para>

        <para>
        <programlisting>.cgi to: &lt;perl install directory&gt;\perl.exe %s
        %s .pl to: &lt;perl install directory&gt;\perl.exe %s %s
        GET,HEAD,POST</programlisting>

        Change the path to Perl to match your install, of course.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section id="addlwintips">
      <title>Additional Windows Tips</title>

      <tip>
        <para>From Andrew Pearson: 
        <blockquote>
          <para>You can make Bugzilla work with Personal Web Server for
          Windows 98 and higher, as well as for IIS 4.0. Microsoft has
          information available at 
          <ulink
          url=" http://support.microsoft.com/support/kb/articles/Q231/9/98.ASP">
          http://support.microsoft.com/support/kb/articles/Q231/9/98.ASP</ulink>
          </para>

          <para>Basically you need to add two String Keys in the registry at
          the following location:</para>

          <para>
            <programlisting>
            HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Services\W3SVC\Parameters\ScriptMap</programlisting>
          </para>

          <para>The keys should be called ".pl" and ".cgi", and both should
          have a value something like: 
          <command>c:/perl/bin/perl.exe "%s" "%s"</command>
          </para>

          <para>The KB article only talks about .pl, but it goes into more
          detail and provides a perl test script.</para>
        </blockquote>
        </para>
      </tip>

      <tip>
        <para>If attempting to run Bugzilla 2.12 or older, you will need to
        remove encrypt() calls from the Perl source. This is 
        <emphasis>not necessary</emphasis>

        for Bugzilla 2.13 and later, which includes the current release,
        Bugzilla &amp;bz-ver;. 
        <example>
          <title>Removing encrypt() for Windows NT Bugzilla version 2.12 or
          earlier</title>

          <para>Replace this: 
          <programlisting>SendSQL("SELECT encrypt(" . SqlQuote($enteredpwd) .
          ", " . SQLQuote(substr($realcryptpwd, 0, 2)) . ")"); my
          $enteredcryptpwd = FetchOneColumn();</programlisting>

          with this: 
          <programlisting>my $enteredcryptpwd = $enteredpwd</programlisting>

          in cgi.pl.</para>
        </example>
        </para>
      </tip>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="osx">
    <title>Mac OS X Installation Notes</title>

    <para>There are a lot of common libraries and utilities out there that
    Apple did not include with Mac OS X, but which run perfectly well on it.
    The GD library, which Bugzilla needs to do bug graphs, is one of
    these.</para>

    <para>The easiest way to get a lot of these is with a program called
    Fink, which is similar in nature to the CPAN installer, but installs
    common GNU utilities. Fink is available from
    &lt;http://sourceforge.net/projects/fink/&gt;.</para>

    <para>Follow the instructions for setting up Fink. Once it's installed,
    you'll want to run the following as root: 
    <command>fink install gd</command>
    </para>

    <para>It will prompt you for a number of dependencies, type 'y' and hit
    enter to install all of the dependencies. Then watch it work.</para>

    <para>To prevent creating conflicts with the software that Apple installs
    by default, Fink creates its own directory tree at /sw where it installs
    most of the software that it installs. This means your libraries and
    headers for libgd will be at /sw/lib and /sw/include instead of /usr/lib
    and /usr/local/include. Because of these changed locations for the
    libraries, the Perl GD module will not install directly via CPAN, because it
    looks for the specific paths instead of getting them from your
    environment. But there's a way around that :-)</para>

    <para>Instead of typing 
    <quote>install GD</quote>
    at the 
    <prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt>
    prompt, type 
    <command>look GD</command>. 
    This should go through the motions of downloading the latest version of
    the GD module, then it will open a shell and drop you into the build
    directory. Apply <ulink url="../sgml/gd-makefile.patch">this patch</ulink> 
    to the Makefile.PL file (save the
    patch into a file and use the command 
    <command>patch &lt; patchfile</command>.)
    </para>
    
    <para>Then, run these commands to finish the installation of the GD
    module: 
    <simplelist>
      <member>
        <command>perl Makefile.PL</command>
      </member>

      <member>
        <command>make</command>
      </member>

      <member>
        <command>make test</command>
      </member>

      <member>
        <command>make install</command>
      </member>

      <member>And don't forget to run 
      <command>exit</command>

      to get back to CPAN.</member>
    </simplelist>
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="troubleshooting">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    
    <para>This section gives solutions to common Bugzilla installation
    problems.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Bundle::Bugzilla makes me upgrade to Perl 5.6.1</title>

      <para>
      Try executing <command>perl -MCPAN -e 'install CPAN'</command>
      and then continuing.
      </para>
      
      <para>
      Certain older versions of the CPAN toolset were somewhat naive about how
      to upgrade Perl modules. When a couple of modules got rolled into the core
      Perl distribution for 5.6.1, CPAN thought that the best way to get those
      modules up to date was to haul down the Perl distribution itself and
      build it. Needless to say, this has caused headaches for just about
      everybody. Upgrading to a newer version of CPAN with the
      commandline above should fix things.
      </para>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>DBD::Sponge::db prepare failed</title>
      
      <para>
        The following error message may appear due to a bug in DBD::mysql
        (over which the Bugzilla team have no control):
      </para>
      
<programlisting><![CDATA[ DBD::Sponge::db prepare failed: Cannot determine NUM_OF_FIELDS at D:/Perl/site/lib/DBD/mysql.pm line 248.
  SV = NULL(0x0) at 0x20fc444
  REFCNT = 1
  FLAGS = (PADBUSY,PADMY)
]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        To fix this, go to 
        <filename>&lt;path-to-perl&gt;/lib/DBD/sponge.pm</filename> 
        in your Perl installation and replace
      </para>
        
<programlisting><![CDATA[ my $numFields;
 if ($attribs->{'NUM_OF_FIELDS'}) {
     $numFields = $attribs->{'NUM_OF_FIELDS'};
 } elsif ($attribs->{'NAME'}) {
     $numFields = @{$attribs->{NAME}};
]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        by
      </para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[ my $numFields;
 if ($attribs->{'NUM_OF_FIELDS'}) {
     $numFields = $attribs->{'NUM_OF_FIELDS'};
 } elsif ($attribs->{'NAMES'}) {
     $numFields = @{$attribs->{NAMES}};
]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        (note the S added to NAME.)      
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="paranoid-security">
      <title>cannot chdir(/var/spool/mqueue)</title>

      <para>If you are installing Bugzilla on SuSE Linux, or some other
      distributions with 
      <quote>paranoid</quote>
      security options, it is possible that the checksetup.pl script may fail
      with the error: 
<programlisting><![CDATA[cannot chdir(/var/spool/mqueue): Permission denied
]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>
      This is because your 
      <filename>/var/spool/mqueue</filename>
      directory has a mode of 
      <quote>drwx------</quote>. Type 
      <command>chmod 755 
      <filename>/var/spool/mqueue</filename>
      </command>
      as root to fix this problem.
      </para>
    </section>    
  </section>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-auto-insert-required-elements:t
sgml-balanced-tag-edit:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-namecase-general:t
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-parent-document:("Bugzilla-Guide.sgml" "book" "chapter")
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-tag-region-if-active:t
End:
-->

